<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
<meta name="date" content="2015-04-10T04:06:07Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:PDFVersion" content="1.7"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:title" content="supplementary.pmd"/>
<meta name="xmp:CreatorTool" content="PageMaker 7.0"/>
<meta name="access_permission:modify_annotations" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_print_degraded" content="true"/>
<meta name="dc:creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="dcterms:created" content="2014-06-05T11:07:38Z"/>
<meta name="Last-Modified" content="2015-04-10T04:06:07Z"/>
<meta name="dcterms:modified" content="2015-04-10T04:06:07Z"/>
<meta name="dc:format" content="application/pdf; version=1.7"/>
<meta name="dc:format" content="application/pdf; version=&quot;1.7 Adobe Extension Level 8&quot;"/>
<meta name="xmpMM:DocumentID" content="1a8d7fd0-eefd-11e3-0000-66c157104585"/>
<meta name="Last-Save-Date" content="2015-04-10T04:06:07Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:creator_tool" content="PageMaker 7.0"/>
<meta name="access_permission:fill_in_form" content="true"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:modified" content="2015-04-10T04:06:07Z"/>
<meta name="meta:save-date" content="2015-04-10T04:06:07Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:encrypted" content="false"/>
<meta name="dc:title" content="supplementary.pmd"/>
<meta name="modified" content="2015-04-10T04:06:07Z"/>
<meta name="Content-Length" content="139748"/>
<meta name="Content-Type" content="application/pdf"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="X-Parsed-By" content="org.apache.tika.parser.DefaultParser"/>
<meta name="X-Parsed-By" content="org.apache.tika.parser.pdf.PDFParser"/>
<meta name="creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="meta:author" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="meta:creation-date" content="2014-06-05T11:07:38Z"/>
<meta name="created" content="Thu Jun 05 16:37:38 IST 2014"/>
<meta name="pdf:PDFExtensionVersion" content="1.7 Adobe Extension Level 8"/>
<meta name="access_permission:extract_for_accessibility" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:assemble_document" content="true"/>
<meta name="xmpTPg:NPages" content="4"/>
<meta name="Creation-Date" content="2014-06-05T11:07:38Z"/>
<meta name="resourceName" content="lebo117.pdf"/>
<meta name="access_permission:extract_content" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_print" content="true"/>
<meta name="Author" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="producer" content="GPL Ghostscript 8.61"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_modify" content="true"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:producer" content="GPL Ghostscript 8.61"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:created" content="2014-06-05T11:07:38Z"/>
<title>supplementary.pmd</title>
</head>
<body><div class="page"><p/>
<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL
</p>
<p>UNIT VI: CHAPTER 1; 1.1, PAGE 6 AT THE END OF FIRST PARA
</p>
<p>Under unfavourable condition the Amoeba withdraws its pseudopodia
and secretes a three-layered hard covering or cyst around itself. This
phenomenon is termed as encystation. When favourable conditions
return, the encysted Amoeba divides by multiple fission and produces
many minute amoeba or pseudopodiospores; the cyst wall bursts out,
and the spores are liberated in the surrounding medium to grow up into
many amoebae. This phenomenon is known as sporulation.
</p>
<p>UNIT VI: CHAPTER 1; 1.1, PAGE 7 AT THE END OF SECOND PARA
</p>
<p>In some organisms, if the body breaks into distinct pieces (fragments)
each fragment grows into an adult capable of producing offspring (e.g.,
Hydra). This is also a mode of asexual reproduction called
fragmentation.
</p>
<p>UNIT VII: CHAPTER 5; PAGE 85 (TO BE GIVEN AS SECTION 5.4)
</p>
<p>POLYGENIC INHERITANCE
</p>
<p>Mendel’s studies mainly described those traits that have distinct alternate
forms such as flower colour which are either purple or white. But if you
look around you will find that there are many traits which are not so
distinct in their occurrence and are spread across a gradient. For example,
in humans we don’t just have tall or short people as two distinct
alternatives but a whole range of possible heights. Such traits are generally
controlled by three or more genes and are thus called as polygenic traits.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>288
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>Besides the involvement of multiple genes polygenic inheritance also takes
into account the influence of environment. Human skin colour is another
classic example for this. In a polygenic trait the phenotype reflects the
contribution of each allele, i.e., the effect of each allele is additive. To
understand this better let us assume that three genes A, B, C control skin
colour in human with the dominant forms A, B and C responsible for dark
skin colour and the recessive forms a, b and c for light skin colour. The
genotype with all the dominant alleles (AABBCC) will have the darkest skin
colour and that with all the recessive alleles (aabbcc) will have the lightest
skin colour. As expected the genotype with three dominant alleles and three
recessive alleles will have an intermediate skin colour. In this manner the
number of each type of alleles in the genotype would determine the darkness
or lightness of the skin in an individual.
</p>
<p>UNIT VII: CHAPTER 5; PAGE 85 (TO BE GIVEN AS SECTION 5.5)
</p>
<p>PLEIOTROPY
</p>
<p>We have so far seen the effect of a gene on a single phenotype or trait.
There are however instances where a single gene can exhibit multiple
phenotypic expression. Such a gene is called a pleiotropic gene. The
underlying mechanism of pleiotropy in most cases is the effect of a gene
on metabolic pathways which contributes towards different phenotypes.
An example of this is the disease phenylketonuria, which occurs in
humans. The disease is caused by mutation in the gene that codes for the
enzyme phenyl alanine hydroxylase (single gene mutation). This manifests
itself through phenotypic expression characterised by mental
retardation and a reduction in hair and skin pigmentation.
</p>
<p>UNIT VII: CHAPTER 5; 5.4, PAGE 86 AFTER SECOND PARA
</p>
<p>SEX DETERMINATION IN HONEY BEE
</p>
<p>The sex determination in honey bee is based on the number of sets of
chromosomes an individual receives. An offspring formed from the union
of a sperm and an egg develops as a female (queen or worker), and an
unfertilised egg develops as a male (drone) by means of parthenogenesis.
This means that the males have half the number of chromosomes than that
of a female. The females are diploid having 32 chromosomes and males are
haploid, i.e., having 16 chromosomes. This is called as haplodiploid sex-
determination system and has special characteristic features such as the
males produce sperms by mitosis (Figure 5.13), they do not have father
and thus cannot have sons, but have a grandfather and can have grandsons.
</p>
<p>Fig.5.13  Sex determination in honey bee
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>289
</p>
<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL
</p>
<p>UNIT VII: CHAPTER 5; 5.6.2, PAGE 89 AFTER FIRST PARA
</p>
<p>COLOUR BLINDNESS
</p>
<p>It is a sex-linked recessive disorder due to defect in either red or green
cone of eye resulting in failure to discriminate between red and green
colour.  This defect is due to mutation in certain genes present in the X
chromosome. It occurs in about 8 per cent of males and only about 0.4
per cent of females. This is because the genes that lead to red-green colour
blindness are on the X chromosome. Males have only one X chromosome
and females have two. The son of a woman who carries the gene has a 50
per cent chance of being colour blind. The mother is not herself colour
blind because the gene is recessive. That means that its effect is suppressed
by her matching dominant normal gene. A daughter will not normally be
colour blind, unless her mother is a carrier and her father is colour blind.
</p>
<p>UNIT VII: CHAPTER 5; 5.6.2, PAGE 90 AFTER SECOND PARA
</p>
<p>THALASSEMIA
</p>
<p>This is also an autosome -linked recessive blood disease transmitted from
parents to the offspring when both the partners are unaffected carrier for
the gene (or heterozygous). The defect could be due to either mutation or
deletion which ultimately results in reduced rate of synthesis of one of the
globin chains (á and â chains) that make up haemoglobin. This causes the
formation of abnormal haemoglobin molecules resulting into anaemia which
is characteristic of the disease. Thalassemia can be classified according to
which chain of the haemoglobin molecule is affected. In á Thalassemia,
production of á globin chain is affected while in â Thalassemia, production
of â globin chain is affected. á Thalassemia is controlled by two closely
linked genes HBA1 and HBA2 on chromosome 16 of each parent and it is
observed due to mutation or deletion of one or more of the four genes. The
more genes affected, the less alpha globin molecules produced. While â
Thalassemia is controlled by a single gene HBB on chromosome 11 of each
parent and occurs due to mutation of one or both the genes. Thalassemia
differs from sickle-cell anaemia in that the former is a quantitative problem
of synthesising too few globin molecules while the latter is a qualitative
problem of synthesising an incorrectly functioning globin.
</p>
<p>UNIT VII: CHAPTER 7; 7.3, PAGE 129 AFTER SECOND PARA
</p>
<p>Embryological support for evolution was also proposed by Ernst Heckel
based upon the observation of certain features during embryonic stage
common to all vertebrates that are absent in adult. For example, the
embryos of all vertebrates including human develop a row of vestigial gill
slit just behind the head but it is a functional organ only in fish and not
found in any other adult vertebrates. However, this proposal was
disapproved on careful study performed by Karl Ernst von Baer. He noted
that embryos never pass through the adult stages of other animals.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>290
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>UNIT X: CHAPTER 13; 13.1, PAGE 221 AT THE END OF FIRST
PARA
</p>
<p>Each organism has an invariably defined range of conditions that it can
tolerate, diversity in the resources it utilises and a distinct functional role
in the ecological system, all these together comprise its niche.
</p>
<p>UNIT X: CHAPTER 15; PAGE 266 IN FOURTH LINE OF 15.2.2
AFTER THE WORD THREATENED
</p>
<p>(organisms facing a very high risk of extinction in the wild in the near
future)
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="acroform"><ol/>
</div>
</body></html>