<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
<meta name="date" content="2015-04-10T04:11:02Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:PDFVersion" content="1.7"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:title" content="MICROBES IN HUMAN WELFARE.pmd"/>
<meta name="xmp:CreatorTool" content="PageMaker 7.0"/>
<meta name="access_permission:modify_annotations" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_print_degraded" content="true"/>
<meta name="dc:creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="dcterms:created" content="2014-06-05T09:00:48Z"/>
<meta name="Last-Modified" content="2015-04-10T04:11:02Z"/>
<meta name="dcterms:modified" content="2015-04-10T04:11:02Z"/>
<meta name="dc:format" content="application/pdf; version=1.7"/>
<meta name="dc:format" content="application/pdf; version=&quot;1.7 Adobe Extension Level 8&quot;"/>
<meta name="xmpMM:DocumentID" content="62a3a684-eeeb-11e3-0000-5e01813d846f"/>
<meta name="Last-Save-Date" content="2015-04-10T04:11:02Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:creator_tool" content="PageMaker 7.0"/>
<meta name="access_permission:fill_in_form" content="true"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:modified" content="2015-04-10T04:11:02Z"/>
<meta name="meta:save-date" content="2015-04-10T04:11:02Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:encrypted" content="false"/>
<meta name="dc:title" content="MICROBES IN HUMAN WELFARE.pmd"/>
<meta name="modified" content="2015-04-10T04:11:02Z"/>
<meta name="Content-Length" content="11691241"/>
<meta name="Content-Type" content="application/pdf"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="X-Parsed-By" content="org.apache.tika.parser.DefaultParser"/>
<meta name="X-Parsed-By" content="org.apache.tika.parser.pdf.PDFParser"/>
<meta name="creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="meta:author" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="meta:creation-date" content="2014-06-05T09:00:48Z"/>
<meta name="created" content="Thu Jun 05 14:30:48 IST 2014"/>
<meta name="pdf:PDFExtensionVersion" content="1.7 Adobe Extension Level 8"/>
<meta name="access_permission:extract_for_accessibility" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:assemble_document" content="true"/>
<meta name="xmpTPg:NPages" content="12"/>
<meta name="Creation-Date" content="2014-06-05T09:00:48Z"/>
<meta name="resourceName" content="lebo110.pdf"/>
<meta name="access_permission:extract_content" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_print" content="true"/>
<meta name="Author" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="producer" content="GPL Ghostscript 8.61"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_modify" content="true"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:producer" content="GPL Ghostscript 8.61"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:created" content="2014-06-05T09:00:48Z"/>
<title>MICROBES IN HUMAN WELFARE.pmd</title>
</head>
<body><div class="page"><p/>
<p>Besides macroscopic plants and animals, microbes are
</p>
<p>the major components of biological systems on this earth.
</p>
<p>You have studied about the diversity of living organisms
</p>
<p>in Class XI. Do you remember which Kingdoms among
</p>
<p>the living organisms contain micro-organisms? Which are
</p>
<p>the ones that are only microscopic? Microbes are present
</p>
<p>everywhere – in soil, water, air, inside our bodies and that
</p>
<p>of other animals and plants. They are present even at sites
</p>
<p>where no other life-form could possibly exist–sites such
</p>
<p>as deep inside the geysers (thermal vents) where the
</p>
<p>temperature may be as high as 1000C, deep in the soil,
</p>
<p>under the layers of snow several metres thick, and in highly
</p>
<p>acidic environments. Microbes are diverse–protozoa,
</p>
<p>bacteria, fungi and microscopic plant viruses, viroids and
</p>
<p>also prions that are proteinacious infectious agents. Some
</p>
<p>of the microbes are shown in Figures 10.1 and 10.2.
</p>
<p>Microbes like bacteria and many fungi can be grown
</p>
<p>on nutritive media to form colonies (Figure 10.3), that can
</p>
<p>be seen with the naked eyes.  Such cultures are useful in
</p>
<p>studies on micro-organisms.
</p>
<p>CHAPTER 10
</p>
<p>MICROBES IN HUMAN WELFARE
</p>
<p>10.1 Microbes in Household
</p>
<p>Products
</p>
<p>10.2 Microbes in Industrial
</p>
<p>Products
</p>
<p>10.3 Microbes in Sewage
</p>
<p>Treatment
</p>
<p>10.4 Microbes in Production of
</p>
<p>Biogas
</p>
<p>10.5 Microbes as Biocontrol
</p>
<p>Agents
</p>
<p>10.6 Microbes as Biofertilisers
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>180
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>(a)
</p>
<p>(b)
</p>
<p>(c)
</p>
<p>(a) (b)
</p>
<p>Figure 10.3 (a) Colonies of bacteria growing in a petri dish;
(b) Fungal colony growing in a petri dish
</p>
<p>(a) (b)
</p>
<p>(c)
Figure10.1 Bacteria: (a) Rod-shaped,
magnified 1500X; (b) Spherical
shaped, magnified1500X; (c) A rod-
shaped bacterium showing flagella,
magnified 50,000X
</p>
<p>Figure 10.2 Viruses: (a) A bacteriophage; (b)
Adenovirus which causes respiratory
infections; (c) Rod-shaped Tobacco
Mosaic Virus (TMV). Magnified about
1,00,000–1,50,000X
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>181
</p>
<p>MICROBES IN HUMAN WELFARE
</p>
<p> In chapter 8, you have read that microbes cause a large number of
</p>
<p>diseases in human beings. They also cause diseases in animals and plants.
</p>
<p>But this should not make you think that all microbes are harmful; several
</p>
<p>microbes are useful to man in diverse ways. Some of the most important
</p>
<p>contributions of microbes to human welfare are discussed in this chapter.
</p>
<p>10.1 MICROBES IN HOUSEHOLD PRODUCTS
</p>
<p>You would be surprised to know that we use microbes or products
</p>
<p>derived from them everyday. A common example is the production of
</p>
<p>curd from milk. Micro-organisms such as Lactobacillus and others
</p>
<p>commonly called lactic acid bacteria (LAB) grow in milk and convert it
</p>
<p>to curd. During growth, the LAB produce acids that coagulate and
</p>
<p>partially digest the milk proteins. A small amount of curd added to the
</p>
<p>fresh milk as inoculum or starter contain millions of LAB, which at
</p>
<p>suitable temperatures multiply, thus converting milk to curd, which
</p>
<p>also improves its nutritional quality by increasing vitamin B
12
</p>
<p>. In our
</p>
<p>stomach too, the LAB play very beneficial role in checking disease-
</p>
<p>causing microbes.
</p>
<p>The dough, which is used for making foods such as dosa and idli  is
</p>
<p>also fermented by bacteria. The puffed-up appearance of dough is due to
</p>
<p>the production of  CO
2
 gas.  Can you tell which metabolic pathway is
</p>
<p>taking place resulting in the formation of CO
2
? Where do you think the
</p>
<p>bacteria for these fermentations came from?  Similarly the dough, which
</p>
<p>is used for making bread, is fermented using baker’s yeast
</p>
<p>(Saccharomyces cerevisiae). A number of traditional drinks and foods
</p>
<p>are also made by fermentation by the microbes. ‘Toddy’, a traditional
</p>
<p>drink of some parts of southern India is made by fermenting sap from
</p>
<p>palms. Microbes are also used to ferment fish, soyabean and bamboo-
</p>
<p>shoots to make foods. Cheese, is one of the oldest food items in which
</p>
<p>microbes were used. Different varieties of cheese are known by their
</p>
<p>characteristic texture, flavour and taste, the specificity coming from the
</p>
<p>microbes used. For example, the large holes in ‘Swiss cheese’ are due to
</p>
<p>production of a large amount of CO
2
 by a bacterium named
</p>
<p>Propionibacterium sharmanii.  The ‘Roquefort cheese’ are ripened by
</p>
<p>growing a specific fungi on them, which gives them a particular flavour.
</p>
<p>10.2 MICROBES IN INDUSTRIAL PRODUCTS
</p>
<p>Even in industry, microbes are used to synthesise a number of products
</p>
<p>valuable to human beings. Beverages and antibiotics are some examples.
</p>
<p>Production on an industrial scale, requires growing microbes in very large
</p>
<p>vessels called fermentors (Figure 10.4).
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>182
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>10.2.1 Fermented Beverages
</p>
<p>Microbes especially yeasts have been used from
</p>
<p>time immemorial for the production of beverages
</p>
<p>like wine, beer, whisky, brandy or rum. For this
</p>
<p>purpose the same yeast Saccharomyces
</p>
<p>cerevisiae used for bread-making and
</p>
<p>commonly called brewer’s yeast, is used for
</p>
<p>fermenting malted cereals and fruit juices, to
</p>
<p>produce ethanol. Do you recollect the metabolic
</p>
<p>reactions, which result in the production of
</p>
<p>ethanol by yeast? Depending on the type of the
</p>
<p>raw material used for fermentation and the type
</p>
<p>of processing (with or without distillation)
</p>
<p>different types of alcoholic drinks are obtained.
</p>
<p>Wine and beer are produced without distillation
</p>
<p>whereas whisky, brandy and rum are produced
</p>
<p>by distillation of the fermented broth. The
</p>
<p>photograph of a fermentation plant is shown in
</p>
<p>Figure 10.5.
</p>
<p>10.2.2 Antibiotics
</p>
<p>Antibiotics produced by microbes are regarded
</p>
<p>as one of the most significant discoveries of the
</p>
<p>twentieth century and have greatly contributed
</p>
<p>towards the welfare of the human society. Anti is
</p>
<p>a Greek word that means ‘against’, and bio means
</p>
<p>‘life’, together they mean ‘against life’ (in the
</p>
<p>context of disease causing organisms); whereas with reference to human
</p>
<p>beings, they are ‘pro life’ and not against. Antibiotics are chemical
</p>
<p>substances, which are produced by some microbes and can kill or retard
</p>
<p>the growth of other (disease-causing) microbes.
</p>
<p>You are familiar with the commonly used antibiotic Penicillin. Do you
</p>
<p>know that Penicillin was the first antibiotic to be discovered, and it was a
</p>
<p>chance discovery?  Alexander Fleming while working on Staphylococci
</p>
<p>bacteria, once observed a mould growing in one of his unwashed culture
</p>
<p>plates around which Staphylococci could not grow. He found out that it
</p>
<p>was due to a chemical produced by the mould and he named it Penicillin
</p>
<p>after the mould Penicillium notatum. However, its full potential as an
</p>
<p>effective antibiotic was established much later by Ernest Chain and
</p>
<p>Howard Florey. This antibiotic  was extensively used to treat American
</p>
<p>soldiers wounded in World War II. Fleming, Chain and Florey were awarded
</p>
<p>the Nobel Prize in 1945, for this discovery.
</p>
<p>Figure 10.5 Fermentation Plant
</p>
<p>Figure 10.4 Fermentors
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>183
</p>
<p>MICROBES IN HUMAN WELFARE
</p>
<p>After Penicillin, other antibiotics were also purified from other
</p>
<p>microbes. Can you name some other antibiotics and find out their
</p>
<p>sources? Antibiotics have greatly improved our capacity to treat deadly
</p>
<p>diseases such as plague, whooping cough (kali khansi ), diphtheria (gal
</p>
<p>ghotu) and leprosy (kusht rog), which used to kill millions all over the
</p>
<p>globe. Today, we cannot imagine a world without antibiotics.
</p>
<p>10.2.3 Chemicals, Enzymes and other Bioactive Molecules
</p>
<p>Microbes are also used for commercial and industrial production of
</p>
<p>certain chemicals like organic acids, alcohols and enzymes. Examples of
</p>
<p>acid producers are Aspergillus niger (a fungus) of citric acid, Acetobacter
</p>
<p>aceti (a bacterium) of acetic acid; Clostridium butylicum (a bacterium) of
</p>
<p>butyric acid and Lactobacillus (a bacterium) of lactic acid.
</p>
<p>Yeast (Saccharomyces cerevisiae) is used for commercial production
</p>
<p>of ethanol. Microbes are also used for production of enzymes. Lipases are
</p>
<p>used in detergent formulations and are helpful in removing oily stains
</p>
<p>from the laundry. You must have noticed that bottled fruit juices bought
</p>
<p>from the market are clearer as compared to those made at home. This is
</p>
<p>because the bottled juices are clarified by the use of pectinases and
</p>
<p>proteases. Streptokinase produced by the bacterium Streptococcus and
</p>
<p>modified by genetic engineering is used as a ‘clot buster’ for removing
</p>
<p>clots from the blood vessels of patients who have undergone myocardial
</p>
<p>infaction leading to heart attack.
</p>
<p>Another bioactive molecule, cyclosporin A, that is used as an
</p>
<p>immunosuppressive agent in organ-transplant patients, is produced by
</p>
<p>the fungus Trichoderma polysporum. Statins produced by the yeast
</p>
<p>Monascus purpureus have been commercialised as blood-cholesterol
</p>
<p>lowering agents. It acts by competitively inhibiting the enzyme responsible
</p>
<p>for synthesis of cholesterol.
</p>
<p>10.3 MICROBES IN SEWAGE TREATMENT
</p>
<p>We know that large quantities of waste water are generated everyday in
</p>
<p>cities and towns. A major component of this waste water is human excreta.
</p>
<p>This municipal waste-water is also called sewage. It contains large
</p>
<p>amounts of organic matter and microbes. Many of which are pathogenic.
</p>
<p>Have you ever wondered where this huge quantity of sewage or urban
</p>
<p>waste water is disposed off daily? This cannot be discharged into natural
</p>
<p>water bodies like rivers and streams directly – you can understand why.
</p>
<p>Before disposal, hence, sewage is treated in sewage treatment plants (STPs)
</p>
<p>to make it less polluting. Treatment of waste water is done by the
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>184
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>heterotrophic microbes naturally present in
</p>
<p>the sewage. This treatment is carried out in
</p>
<p>two stages:
</p>
<p>Primary treatment : These treatment
</p>
<p>steps basically involve physical removal of
</p>
<p>particles – large and small – from the sewage
</p>
<p>through filtration and sedimentation. These
</p>
<p>are removed in stages; initially, floating debris
</p>
<p>is removed by sequential filtration. Then the
</p>
<p>grit (soil and small pebbles) are removed by
</p>
<p>sedimentation. All solids that settle form the
</p>
<p>primary sludge, and the supernatant forms
</p>
<p>the effluent.  The effluent from the primary
</p>
<p>settling tank is taken for secondary treatment.
</p>
<p>Secondary treatment or Biological treatment : The primary
</p>
<p>effluent is passed into large aeration tanks (Figure 10.6) where it is
</p>
<p>constantly agitated mechanically and air is pumped into it. This allows
</p>
<p>vigorous growth of useful aerobic microbes into flocs (masses of
</p>
<p>bacteria associated with fungal filaments to form mesh like
</p>
<p>structures). While growing, these microbes consume the major part
</p>
<p>of the organic matter in the effluent. This significantly reduces the
</p>
<p>BOD (biochemical oxygen demand) of the effluent. BOD refers to
</p>
<p>the amount of the oxygen that would be consumed if all the organic
</p>
<p>matter in one liter of water were oxidised by bacteria. The sewage
</p>
<p>water is treated till the BOD is reduced. The BOD test measures the
</p>
<p>rate of uptake of oxygen by micro-organisms in a sample of water
</p>
<p>and thus, indirectly, BOD is a measure of the organic matter present
</p>
<p>in the water. The greater the BOD of waste water, more is its polluting
</p>
<p>potential.
</p>
<p>Once the BOD of sewage or waste water is reduced significantly, the
</p>
<p>effluent is then passed into a settling tank where the bacterial ‘flocs’ are
</p>
<p>allowed to sediment. This sediment is called activated sludge. A small
</p>
<p>part of the activated sludge is pumped back into the aeration tank to
</p>
<p>serve as the inoculum. The remaining major part of the sludge is pumped
</p>
<p>into large tanks called anaerobic sludge digesters. Here, other kinds
</p>
<p>of bacteria, which grow anaerobically, digest the bacteria and the fungi
</p>
<p>in the sludge. During this digestion, bacteria produce a mixture of gases
</p>
<p>such as methane, hydrogen sulphide and carbon dioxide. These gases
</p>
<p>form biogas and can be used as source of energy as it is inflammable.
</p>
<p>The effluent from the secondary treatment plant is generally released
</p>
<p>into natural water bodies like rivers and streams. An aerial view of such
</p>
<p>a plant is shown in Figure 10.7.
</p>
<p>Figure 10.6 Secondary treatment
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>185
</p>
<p>MICROBES IN HUMAN WELFARE
</p>
<p>You can appreciate how microbes play a major
</p>
<p>role in treating millions of gallons of waste water
</p>
<p>everyday across the globe. This methodology has
</p>
<p>been practiced for more than a century now, in
</p>
<p>almost all parts of the world. Till date, no man-
</p>
<p>made technology has been able to rival the
</p>
<p>microbial treatment of sewage.
</p>
<p>You are aware that due to increasing
</p>
<p>urbanisation, sewage is being produced in much
</p>
<p>larger quantities than ever before. However the
</p>
<p>number of sewage treatment plants has not
</p>
<p>increased enough to treat such large quantities.
</p>
<p>So the untreated sewage is often discharged directly into rivers leading to
</p>
<p>their pollution and increase in water-borne diseases.
</p>
<p>The Ministry of Environment and Forests has initiated Ganga Action
</p>
<p>Plan and Yamuna Action Plan to save these major rivers of our country
</p>
<p>from pollution. Under these plans, it is proposed to build a large number
</p>
<p>of sewage treatment plants so that only treated sewage may be discharged
</p>
<p>in the rivers. A visit to a sewage treatment plant situated in any place
</p>
<p>near you would be a very interesting and educating experience.
</p>
<p>10.4 MICROBES IN PRODUCTION OF BIOGAS
</p>
<p>Biogas is a mixture of gases (containing predominantly methane) produced
</p>
<p>by the microbial activity and which may be used as fuel. You have learnt
</p>
<p>that microbes produce different types of gaseous end-products during
</p>
<p>growth and metabolism. The type of the gas produced depends upon the
</p>
<p>microbes and the organic substrates they utilise. In the examples cited in
</p>
<p>relation to fermentation of dough, cheese making and production of
</p>
<p>beverages, the main gas produced was CO
2.
. However, certain bacteria,
</p>
<p>which grow anaerobically on cellulosic material, produce large amount
</p>
<p>of methane along with CO
2
 and H
</p>
<p>2
. These bacteria are collectively called
</p>
<p>methanogens, and one such common bacterium is Methanobacterium.
</p>
<p>These bacteria are commonly found in the anaerobic sludge during
</p>
<p>sewage treatment. These bacteria are also present in the rumen (a part of
</p>
<p>stomach) of cattle. A lot of cellulosic material present in the food of cattle
</p>
<p>is also present in the rumen. In rumen, these bacteria help in the
</p>
<p>breakdown of cellulose and play an important role in the nutrition of
</p>
<p>cattle. Do you think we, human beings, are able to digest the celluose
</p>
<p>present in our foods? Thus, the excreta (dung) of cattle, commonly called
</p>
<p>gobar, is rich in these bacteria. Dung can be used for generation of biogas,
</p>
<p>commonly called gobar gas.
</p>
<p>The biogas plant consists of a concrete tank (10-15 feet deep) in which
</p>
<p>bio-wastes are collected and a slurry of dung is fed. A floating cover is
</p>
<p>Figure 10.7 An aerial view of a sewage plant
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>186
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>placed over the slurry, which
</p>
<p>keeps on rising as the gas is
</p>
<p>produced in the tank due to the
</p>
<p>microbial activity. The biogas
</p>
<p>plant has an outlet, which is
</p>
<p>connected to a pipe to supply
</p>
<p>biogas to nearby houses. The
</p>
<p>spent slurry is removed through
</p>
<p>another outlet and may be used
</p>
<p>as fertiliser. Cattle dung is
</p>
<p>available in large quantities in
</p>
<p>rural areas where cattle are used
</p>
<p>for a variety of purposes. So
</p>
<p>biogas plants are more often
</p>
<p>built in rural areas. The biogas
</p>
<p>thus produced is used for
</p>
<p>cooking and lighting. The
</p>
<p>picture of a biogas plant is
</p>
<p>shown in Figure 10.8. The
</p>
<p>technology of biogas production
</p>
<p>was developed in India mainly
</p>
<p>due to the efforts of Indian Agricultural Research Institute (IARI) and
</p>
<p>Khadi and Village Industries Commission (KVIC). If your school is situated
</p>
<p>in a village or near a village, it would be very interesting to enquire if there
</p>
<p>are any biogas plants nearby.  Visit the biogas plant and learn more about
</p>
<p>it from the people who are actually managing it.
</p>
<p>10.5 MICROBES AS BIOCONTROL AGENTS
</p>
<p>Biocontrol refers to the use of biological methods for controlling plant
</p>
<p>diseases and pests. In modern society, these problems have been tackled
</p>
<p>increasingly by the use of chemicals – by use of insecticides and pesticides.
</p>
<p>These chemicals are toxic and extremely harmful, to human beings and
</p>
<p>animals alike, and have been polluting our environment (soil, ground
</p>
<p>water), fruits, vegetables and crop plants. Our soil is also polluted through
</p>
<p>our use of weedicides to remove weeds.
</p>
<p>Biological control of pests and diseases: In agriculture, there is a
</p>
<p>method of controlling pests that relies on natural predation rather than
</p>
<p>introduced chemicals. A key belief of the organic farmer is that biodiversity
</p>
<p>furthers health. The more variety a landscape has, the more sustainable
</p>
<p>it is. The organic farmer, therefore, works to create a system where the
</p>
<p>insects that are sometimes called pests are not eradicated, but instead
</p>
<p>are kept at manageable levels by a complex system of checks and balances
</p>
<p>within a living and vibrant ecosystem. Contrary to the ‘conventional’
</p>
<p>farming practices which often use chemical methods to kill both useful
</p>
<p>Figure 10.8 A typical biogas plant
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>187
</p>
<p>MICROBES IN HUMAN WELFARE
</p>
<p>and harmful life forms indiscriminately, this is a holistic approach that
</p>
<p>seeks to develop an understanding of the webs of interaction between the
</p>
<p>myriad of organisms that constitute the field fauna and flora. The organic
</p>
<p>farmer holds the view that the eradication of the creatures that are often
</p>
<p>described as pests is not only possible, but also undesirable, for without
</p>
<p>them the beneficial predatory and parasitic insects which depend upon
</p>
<p>them as food or hosts would not be able to survive. Thus, the use of
</p>
<p>biocontrol measures will greatly reduce our dependence on toxic chemicals
</p>
<p>and pesticides. An important part of the biological farming approach is
</p>
<p>to become familiar with the various life forms that inhabit the field,
</p>
<p>predators as well as pests, and also their life cycles, patterns of feeding
</p>
<p>and the habitats that they prefer. This will help develop appropriate means
</p>
<p>of biocontrol.
</p>
<p>The very familiar beetle with red and black markings – the Ladybird,
</p>
<p>and Dragonflies are useful to get rid of aphids and mosquitoes,
</p>
<p>respectively. An example of microbial biocontrol agents that can be
</p>
<p>introduced in order to control butterfly caterpillars is the bacteria Bacillus
</p>
<p>thuringiensis (often written as Bt ). These are available in sachets as dried
</p>
<p>spores which are mixed with water and sprayed onto vulnerable plants
</p>
<p>such as brassicas and fruit trees, where these are eaten by the insect
</p>
<p>larvae. In the gut of the larvae, the toxin is released and the larvae get
</p>
<p>killed. The bacterial disease will kill the caterpillars, but leave other insects
</p>
<p>unharmed. Because of the development of methods of genetic engineering
</p>
<p>in the last decade or so, the scientists have introduced B. thuringiensis
</p>
<p>toxin genes into plants. Such plants are resistant to attack by insect pests.
</p>
<p>Bt-cotton is one such example, which is being cultivated in some states
</p>
<p>of our country. You will learn more about this in chapter 12.
</p>
<p>A biological control being developed for use in the treatment of plant
</p>
<p>disease is the fungus Trichoderma. Trichoderma species are free-living
</p>
<p>fungi that are very common in the root ecosystems. They are effective
</p>
<p>biocontrol agents of several plant pathogens.
</p>
<p>Baculoviruses are pathogens that attack insects and other arthropods.
</p>
<p>The majority of baculoviruses used as biological control agents are in the
</p>
<p>genus Nucleopolyhedrovirus. These viruses are excellent candidates for
</p>
<p>species-specific, narrow spectrum insecticidal applications. They have
</p>
<p>been shown to have no negative impacts on plants, mammals, birds, fish
</p>
<p>or even on non-target insects. This is especially desirable when beneficial
</p>
<p>insects are being conserved to aid in an overall integrated pest
</p>
<p>management (IPM) programme, or when an ecologically sensitive area is
</p>
<p>being treated.
</p>
<p>10.6 MICROBES AS BIOFERTILISERS
</p>
<p>With our present day life styles environmental pollution is a major cause
</p>
<p>of concern. The use of the chemical fertilisers to meet the ever-increasing
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>188
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>demand of agricultural produce has contributed significantly to
</p>
<p>this pollution. Of course,  we have now realised that there are problems
</p>
<p>associated with the overuse of chemical fertilisers and there is a
</p>
<p>large pressure to switch to organic farming – the use of biofertilisers.
</p>
<p>Biofertilisers  are organisms that enrich the nutrient quality of the soil.
</p>
<p>The main sources of biofertilisers are bacteria, fungi and cyanobacteria.
</p>
<p>You have studied about the nodules on the roots of leguminous plants
</p>
<p>formed by the symbiotic association of Rhizobium. These bacteria fix
</p>
<p>atmospheric nitrogen into organic forms, which is used by the plant as
</p>
<p>nutrient. Other bacteria can fix atmospheric nitrogen while free-living in
</p>
<p>the soil (examples Azospirillum and Azotobacter), thus enriching the
</p>
<p>nitrogen content of the soil.
</p>
<p>Fungi are also known to form symbiotic associations with plants
</p>
<p>(mycorrhiza). Many members of the genus Glomus  form mycorrhiza.
</p>
<p>The fungal symbiont in these associations absorbs phosphorus from
</p>
<p>soil and passes it to the plant. Plants having such associations show
</p>
<p>other benefits also, such as resistance to root-borne pathogens, tolerance
</p>
<p>to salinity and drought, and an overall increase in plant growth and
</p>
<p>development. Can you tell what advantage the fungus derives from
</p>
<p>this association?
</p>
<p>Cyanobacteria are autotrophic microbes widely distributed in aquatic
</p>
<p>and terrestrial environments many of which can fix atmospheric nitrogen,
</p>
<p>e.g. Anabaena, Nostoc, Oscillatoria, etc. In paddy fields, cyanobacteria
</p>
<p>serve as an important biofertiliser. Blue green algae also add organic matter
</p>
<p>to the soil and increase its fertility. Currently, in our country, a number
</p>
<p>of biofertilisers are available commercially in the market and farmers use
</p>
<p>these regularly in their fields to replenish soil nutrients and to reduce
</p>
<p>dependence on chemical fertilisers.
</p>
<p>SUMMARY
</p>
<p>Microbes are a very important component of life on earth. Not all
</p>
<p>microbes are pathogenic. Many microbes are very useful to human
</p>
<p>beings. We use microbes and microbially derived products almost every
</p>
<p>day. Bacteria called lactic acid bacteria (LAB) grow in milk to convert it
</p>
<p>into curd. The dough, which is used to make bread, is fermented by
</p>
<p>yeast called Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Certain dishes such as idli and
</p>
<p>dosa, are made from dough fermented by microbes. Bacteria and fungi
</p>
<p>are used to impart particular texture, taste and flavor to cheese. Microbes
</p>
<p>are used to produce industrial products like lactic acid, acetic acid
</p>
<p>and alcohol, which are used in a variety of processes in the industry.
</p>
<p>Antibiotics like penicillins produced by useful microbes are used to kill
</p>
<p>disease-causing harmful microbes. Antibiotics have played a major role
</p>
<p>in controlling infectious diseases like diphtheria, whooping cough and
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>189
</p>
<p>MICROBES IN HUMAN WELFARE
</p>
<p>EXERCISES
</p>
<p>1. Bacteria cannot be seen with the naked eyes, but these can be seen
</p>
<p>with the help of a microscope. If you have to carry a sample from your
</p>
<p>home to your biology laboratory to demonstrate the presence of microbes
</p>
<p>under a microscope, which sample would you carry and why?
</p>
<p>2. Give examples to prove that microbes release gases during metabolism.
</p>
<p>3. In which food would you find lactic acid bacteria? Mention some of
</p>
<p>their useful applications.
</p>
<p>4. Name some traditional Indian foods made of wheat, rice and Bengal
</p>
<p>gram (or their products) which involve use of microbes.
</p>
<p>5. In which way have microbes played a major role in controlling diseases
</p>
<p>caused by harmful bacteria?
</p>
<p>6. Name any two species of fungus, which are used in the production of
</p>
<p>the antibiotics.
</p>
<p>7. What is sewage? In which way can sewage be harmful to us?
</p>
<p>8. What is the key difference between primary and secondary sewage
</p>
<p>treatment?
</p>
<p>9. Do you think microbes can also be used as source of energy? If yes, how?
</p>
<p>10. Microbes can be used to decrease the use of chemical fertilisers and
</p>
<p>pesticides. Explain how this can be accomplished.
</p>
<p>11. Three water samples namely river water, untreated sewage water and
</p>
<p>secondary effluent discharged from a sewage treatment plant were
</p>
<p>subjected to BOD test. The samples were labelled A, B and C; but the
</p>
<p>laboratory attendant did not note which was which.  The BOD values
</p>
<p>of the three samples A, B and C were recorded as 20mg/L, 8mg/L and
</p>
<p>400mg/L, respectively. Which sample of the water is most polluted?
</p>
<p>Can you assign the correct label to each assuming the river water is
</p>
<p>relatively clean?
</p>
<p>pneumonia. For more than a hundred years, microbes are being used
</p>
<p>to treat sewage (waste water) by the process of activated sludge formation
</p>
<p>and this helps in recycling of water in nature. Methanogens produce
</p>
<p>methane (biogas) while degrading plant waste. Biogas produced by
</p>
<p>microbes is used as a source of energy in rural areas. Microbes can also
</p>
<p>be used to kill harmful pests, a process called as biocontrol. The
</p>
<p>biocontrol measures help us to avoid heavy use of toxic pesticides for
</p>
<p>controlling pests. There is a need these days to push for use of
</p>
<p>biofertilisers in place of chemical fertilisers.  It is clear from the diverse
</p>
<p>uses human beings have put microbes to that they play an important
</p>
<p>role in the welfare of human society.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>190
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>12. Find out the name of the microbes from which Cyclosporin A (an
</p>
<p>immunosuppressive drug) and Statins (blood cholesterol lowering
</p>
<p>agents) are obtained.
</p>
<p>13. Find out the role of microbes in the following and discuss it with your teacher.
</p>
<p>(a) Single cell protein (SCP)
</p>
<p>(b) Soil
</p>
<p>14. Arrange the following in the decreasing order (most important first) of
</p>
<p>their importance, for the welfare of human society. Give reasons for
</p>
<p>your answer.
</p>
<p>Biogas, Citric acid, Penicillin and Curd
</p>
<p>15. How do biofertilisers enrich the fertility of the soil?
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="acroform"><ol/>
</div>
</body></html>