<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
<meta name="date" content="2015-04-10T04:06:42Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:PDFVersion" content="1.7"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:title" content="prelims.pmd"/>
<meta name="xmp:CreatorTool" content="PageMaker 7.0"/>
<meta name="access_permission:modify_annotations" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_print_degraded" content="true"/>
<meta name="dc:creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="dcterms:created" content="2015-02-27T07:12:36Z"/>
<meta name="Last-Modified" content="2015-04-10T04:06:42Z"/>
<meta name="dcterms:modified" content="2015-04-10T04:06:42Z"/>
<meta name="dc:format" content="application/pdf; version=1.7"/>
<meta name="dc:format" content="application/pdf; version=&quot;1.7 Adobe Extension Level 8&quot;"/>
<meta name="xmpMM:DocumentID" content="8169d563-c0ab-11e4-0000-fc21d64d3817"/>
<meta name="Last-Save-Date" content="2015-04-10T04:06:42Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:creator_tool" content="PageMaker 7.0"/>
<meta name="access_permission:fill_in_form" content="true"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:modified" content="2015-04-10T04:06:42Z"/>
<meta name="meta:save-date" content="2015-04-10T04:06:42Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:encrypted" content="false"/>
<meta name="dc:title" content="prelims.pmd"/>
<meta name="modified" content="2015-04-10T04:06:42Z"/>
<meta name="Content-Length" content="208468"/>
<meta name="Content-Type" content="application/pdf"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="X-Parsed-By" content="org.apache.tika.parser.DefaultParser"/>
<meta name="X-Parsed-By" content="org.apache.tika.parser.pdf.PDFParser"/>
<meta name="creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="meta:author" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="meta:creation-date" content="2015-02-27T07:12:36Z"/>
<meta name="created" content="Fri Feb 27 12:42:36 IST 2015"/>
<meta name="pdf:PDFExtensionVersion" content="1.7 Adobe Extension Level 8"/>
<meta name="access_permission:extract_for_accessibility" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:assemble_document" content="true"/>
<meta name="xmpTPg:NPages" content="10"/>
<meta name="Creation-Date" content="2015-02-27T07:12:36Z"/>
<meta name="resourceName" content="lebo1ps.pdf"/>
<meta name="access_permission:extract_content" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_print" content="true"/>
<meta name="Author" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="producer" content="GPL Ghostscript 8.61"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_modify" content="true"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:producer" content="GPL Ghostscript 8.61"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:created" content="2015-02-27T07:12:36Z"/>
<title>prelims.pmd</title>
</head>
<body><div class="page"><p/>
<p>BIOLOGYBIOLOGYBIOLOGYBIOLOGYBIOLOGY
TEXTBOOK FOR CLASS XIITEXTBOOK FOR CLASS XIITEXTBOOK FOR CLASS XIITEXTBOOK FOR CLASS XIITEXTBOOK FOR CLASS XII
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>First Edition
December 2006 Pausa 1928
</p>
<p>Reprinted
November 2007 Kartika 1929
</p>
<p>January  2009  Pausa 1930
</p>
<p>December 2009  Pausa 1931
</p>
<p>January 2011  Magha 1932
</p>
<p>January 2012  Magha  1933
</p>
<p>November 2012  Kartika 1934
</p>
<p>November 2013  Kartika 1935
</p>
<p>December 2014  Pausa 1936
</p>
<p>PD 255T RPS
</p>
<p>© National Council of Educational
Research and Training, 2006
</p>
<p>` 170.00
</p>
<p>Printed on 80 GSM paper with NCERT
</p>
<p>watermark
</p>
<p>Published at the Publication Division by the
Secretary, National Council of Educational
Research and Training, Sri Aurobindo Marg,
New Delhi 110 016 and printed at Deep
Trading Co. (Noida) H-203, Sector-63, Noida
(U.P.)
</p>
<p>ISBN  81-7450-639-X
</p>
<p>ALL RIGHTS RESERVED
</p>
<p>q No part of this publication may be reproduced, stored in a retrieval system
</p>
<p>or transmitted, in any form or by any means, electronic, mechanical,
</p>
<p>photocopying, recording or otherwise without the prior permission of the
</p>
<p>publisher.
</p>
<p>q This book is sold subject to the condition that it shall not, by way of trade,
</p>
<p>be lent,  re-sold, hired out or otherwise disposed of without the publisher’s
</p>
<p>consent, in any form of binding or cover other than that in which it is
</p>
<p>published.
</p>
<p>q The correct price of this publication is the price printed on this page, Any
</p>
<p>revised price indicated by a rubber stamp or by a sticker or by any other
</p>
<p>means is incorrect and should be unacceptable.
</p>
<p>Publication Team
</p>
<p>Head, Publication : N. K. Gupta
Division
</p>
<p>Chief Production : Kalyan Banerjee
Officer
</p>
<p>Chief Editor : Shveta Uppal
</p>
<p>Chief Business : Gautam Ganguly
Manager
</p>
<p>Production Assistant : Rajesh Pippal
</p>
<p>Cover and Layout
</p>
<p>Shweta Rao
</p>
<p>Illustrations
</p>
<p>Lalit Maurya
</p>
<p>OFFICES OF THE PUBLICATION
</p>
<p>DIVISION, NCERT
</p>
<p>NCERT Campus
</p>
<p>Sri Aurobindo Marg
</p>
<p>New  Delhi 110 016 Phone :  011-26562708
</p>
<p>108, 100 Feet Road
</p>
<p>Hosdakere Halli Extension
</p>
<p>Banashankari III Stage
</p>
<p>Bengaluru 560 085 Phone : 080-26725740
</p>
<p>Navjivan Trust Building
</p>
<p>P.O.Navjivan
</p>
<p>Ahmedabad 380 014 Phone :  079-27541446
</p>
<p>CWC Campus
</p>
<p>Opp. Dhankal Bus Stop
</p>
<p>Panihati
</p>
<p>Kolkata 700 114 Phone :  033-25530454
</p>
<p>CWC Complex
</p>
<p>Maligaon
</p>
<p>Guwahati 781 021 Phone :  0361-2674869
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>III
</p>
<p>FOREWORD
</p>
<p>The National Curriculum Framework (NCF) 2005, recommends that children’s life at school
</p>
<p>must be linked to their life outside the school. This principle marks a departure from the
</p>
<p>legacy of bookish learning which continues to shape our system and causes a gap between
</p>
<p>the school, home and community. The syllabi and textbooks developed on the basis of NCF
</p>
<p>signify an attempt to implement this basic idea. They also attempt to discourage rote learning
</p>
<p>and the maintenance of sharp boundaries between different subject areas. We hope these
</p>
<p>measures will take us significantly further in the direction of a child-centred system of
</p>
<p>education outlined in the National Policy on Education (1986).
</p>
<p>The success of this effort depends on the steps that school principals and teachers will
</p>
<p>take to encourage children to reflect on their own learning and to pursue imaginative activities
</p>
<p>and questions. We must recognise that, given space, time and freedom, children generate
</p>
<p>new knowledge by engaging with the information passed on to them by adults. Treating the
</p>
<p>prescribed textbook as the sole basis of examination is one of the key reasons why other
</p>
<p>resources and sites of learning are ignored. Inculcating creativity and initiative is possible
</p>
<p>if we perceive and treat children as participants in learning, not as receivers of a fixed body
</p>
<p>of knowledge.
</p>
<p>These aims imply considerable change in school routines and mode of functioning.
</p>
<p>Flexibility in the daily time-table is as necessary as rigour in implementing the annual
</p>
<p>calendar so that the required number of teaching days are actually devoted to teaching. The
</p>
<p>methods used for teaching and evaluation will also determine how effective this textbook
</p>
<p>proves for making children’s life at school a happy experience, rather than a source of
</p>
<p>stress or boredom. Syllabus designers have tried to address the problem of curricular burden
</p>
<p>by restructuring and reorienting knowledge at different stages with greater consideration
</p>
<p>for child psychology and the time available for teaching. The textbook attempts to enhance
</p>
<p>this endeavour by giving higher priority and space to opportunities for contemplation and
</p>
<p>wondering, discussion in small groups, and activities requiring hands-on experience.
</p>
<p>The National Council of Educational Research and Training (NCERT) appreciates the
</p>
<p>hard work done by the textbook development committee responsible for this book. We
</p>
<p>wish to thank the Chairperson of the advisory group in science and mathematics,
</p>
<p>Professor J.V. Narlikar and the Chief Advisor for this book, Professor K. Muralidhar,
</p>
<p>Department of Zoology, University of Delhi, Delhi for guiding the work of this committee.
</p>
<p>Several teachers contributed to the development of this textbook. We are grateful to their
</p>
<p>principals for making this possible. We are indebted to the institutions and organisations
</p>
<p>which have generously permitted us to draw upon their resources, material and personnel.
</p>
<p>We are especially grateful to the members of the National Monitoring Committee, appointed
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>IV
</p>
<p>by the Department of Secondary and Higher Education, Ministry of Human Resource
</p>
<p>Development under the Chairmanship of Professor Mrinal Miri and Professor G.P. Deshpande,
</p>
<p>for their valuable time and contribution.
</p>
<p>As an organisation committed to systemic reform and continuous improvement in the
</p>
<p>quality of its products, NCERT welcomes comments and suggestions which will enable us to
</p>
<p>undertake further revision and refinement.
</p>
<p>Director
</p>
<p>New Delhi  National Council of Educational
</p>
<p>20 November 2006 Research and Training
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>V
</p>
<p>Biology is the study of life in its entirety. The growth of biology as a natural science during
</p>
<p>the last 1000 years is interesting from many points of view. One feature of this growth is
</p>
<p>changing emphasis. Initially it was description of life forms. Identification, nomenclature,
</p>
<p>classification of all recorded living forms enjoyed the attention of scientists for a long time.
</p>
<p>Description of their habitats and (in the case of animals) their behaviour was included in
</p>
<p>this study. In later years, the focus was physiology and internal morphology or anatomy.
</p>
<p>Darwinian ideas of evolution by natural selection changed the perception completely. Classical
</p>
<p>descriptive and clueless biology found a theoretical framework in the evolutionary theory of
</p>
<p>Darwin.
</p>
<p>In the nineteenth and twentieth centuries, Physics and Chemistry were applied to Biology
</p>
<p>and the new science of Biochemistry soon became the dominant face of biology. On one hand
</p>
<p>Biochemistry was integrating with Physiology, becoming almost synonymous with it. On the
</p>
<p>other hand it gave rise to Structural Biology (structure of biomacromolecules), originally called
</p>
<p>Molecular Biology. The work of Bernal, Pauling, Watson and Crick, Hodgkins, Perutz and Kendrew,
</p>
<p>Delbruck, Luria, Monod, Beadle and Tatum, Lederberg, Brenner, Benzer, Nirenberg, Khorana,
</p>
<p>Mclintock, Sanger, Cohen, Boyer, Kornbergs (father and son), Leder, Chambon and scores of
</p>
<p>others brought in and established a modern version of Molecular Biology dealing with life
</p>
<p>processes at molecular level.
</p>
<p>Physics and Chemistry dominated public perception of science for a long time.
</p>
<p>Daytoday life of man was influenced by developments in Physics, Chemistry and their respective
</p>
<p>manufacturing industries. Slowly and steadily, Biology, not to be left behind, demonstrated
</p>
<p>its utility for human welfare. Medical practice, especially diagnostics, green revolution and
</p>
<p>the newly emerging biotechnology and its success stories made the presence of biology felt
</p>
<p>by the common man. Patent laws brought biology into political domain and commercial value
</p>
<p>of biology became obvious.
</p>
<p>For more than a century, classical and so-called reductionist biology fought artifical
</p>
<p>battles. The fact is both are important. Ecology brought in synthesis of both approaches
</p>
<p>and emphasised integrated understanding of biology. Form and process are both equally
</p>
<p>important. Systems biology, using mathematical tools, is bringing about a modern synthesis
</p>
<p>of both the aspects of Biology.
</p>
<p>The Class XI and XII textbooks in biology essentially were to reflect these threads of
</p>
<p>biological thought. While the Class XI book dealt with morphology, taxonomy, molecular and
</p>
<p>cellular aspects of physiology, the Class XII book deals with the physiological process of
</p>
<p>reproduction in flowering plants and humans, the principles of inheritance, the nature of
</p>
<p>genetic material and its function, the contributions of biology to human welfare, basic
</p>
<p>principles of biotechnological processes and their applications and achievements. The
</p>
<p>Class XII book also relates genes to evolution on one hand and presents ecological interactions,
</p>
<p>behaviour of populations and ecosystems on the other. Most important, the guidelines under
</p>
<p>NCF-2005 have been followed in letter and spirit. The total learning load has been reduced
</p>
<p>PREFACE
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>VI
</p>
<p>considerably and themes like environmental issues, adolescent problems and reproductive
</p>
<p>health have been dealt with in some detail. Studied together, the class XI and class XII
</p>
<p>textbooks in Biology would enable the student to —
</p>
<p>(i) become familiar with the diversity of biological material.
</p>
<p>(ii) appreciate and believe in the Darwinian evolutionary process exhibited by the living
</p>
<p>world.
</p>
<p>(iii) understand the dynamic state of constituents of living bodies, i.e., metabolic
</p>
<p>basis of all physiological processes in plants, animals and microbes.
</p>
<p>(iv) realise the structure and function of genetic material in directing the inherited
</p>
<p>phenotype pattern as well as a mediator of evolutionary process.
</p>
<p>(v) appreciate the profound contributions of biology to human welfare.
</p>
<p>(vi) reflect on the physico-chemical basis of living processes and at the same time
</p>
<p>realise the limitation of reductionism in understanding behaviour of organisms.
</p>
<p>(vii) experience the humbling effect of this realisation that all living organisms are
</p>
<p>related to each other by virtue of shared genetic material.
</p>
<p>(viii) realise that biology is the story of the struggle of living organisms for existence
</p>
<p>and survival.
</p>
<p>One may notice a perceptible change in the writing style. Most of the chapters are written
</p>
<p>in an easy dialogue style engaging the student constantly while some chapters are in the
</p>
<p>form of critical comments on the subject matter. A number of questions have been provided
</p>
<p>at the end of each chapter though answers to some may not be found in the text. Students
</p>
<p>have to read supplementary material, upon advise from the teacher, to answer such questions.
</p>
<p>I am thankful to Professor Krishna Kumar, Director NCERT; Professor G. Ravindra, Joint
</p>
<p>Director, NCERT and Professor Hukum Singh, Head, DESM, NCERT for constant support. I
</p>
<p>must place on record my deep appreciation for Dr B.K. Tripathi, Reader, DESM, NCERT for
</p>
<p>his relentless efforts as coordinator in bringing out the Biology textbook for both the
</p>
<p>Class XI and XII. All the members of the development team, the experts and reviewers, and
</p>
<p>the school teachers have contributed enormously in the preparation of this book. I thank
</p>
<p>them all. I am indeed highly thankful to the members of monitoring committee constituted
</p>
<p>by Ministry of Human Resource Development for their valuable observation that helped in
</p>
<p>the improvement of the book at the final stage. The book is prepared keeping in mind the
</p>
<p>guidelines of the NCF-2005 especially the emphasis on reducing the learning load. We hope that
</p>
<p>the book would meet the expectations of all the stakeholders. All suggestions for further
</p>
<p>improvement are always welcome.
</p>
<p>K. MURALIDHAR
</p>
<p>Department of Zoology Chief Advisor
</p>
<p>University of Delhi Biology Textbook for Class XII
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>VII
</p>
<p>TEXTBOOK DEVELOPMENT COMMITTEE
</p>
<p>CHAIRPERSON, ADVISORY GROUP FOR TEXTBOOKS IN SCIENCE AND MATHEMATICS
</p>
<p>J.V. Narlikar, Emeritus Professor, Inter University Centre for Astronomy and Astrophysics (IUCAA),
Pune University, Pune
</p>
<p>CHIEF ADVISOR
</p>
<p>K. Muralidhar, Professor, Department of Zoology, University of Delhi, Delhi
</p>
<p>MEMBERS
</p>
<p>Ajit Kumar Kavathekar, Reader (Botany), Sri Venkateswara College, University of Delhi, Delhi
</p>
<p>B.B.P. Gupta, Professor, Department of Zoology, North-Eastern Hill University, Shillong
</p>
<p>B.N. Pandey, Principal, Ordinance Factory Higher Secondary School, Dehradun
</p>
<p>C.V. Shimray, Lecturer, Department of Education in Science and Mathematics, NCERT, New Delhi
</p>
<p>Dinesh Kumar, Reader, Department of Education in Science and Mathematics, NCERT, New Delhi
</p>
<p>J.P. Gaur, Professor, Department of Botany, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi
</p>
<p>J.S. Virdi, Reader, Department of Microbiology, University of Delhi, South Campus, New Delhi
</p>
<p>K. Sarath Chandran, Reader (Zoology), Sri Venkateswara College, University of Delhi, Delhi
</p>
<p>L.C. Rai, Professor, Department of Botany, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi
</p>
<p>M.M. Chaturvedi, Professor, Department of Zoology, University of Delhi, Delhi
</p>
<p>N.V.S.R.K. Prasad, Reader (Botany), Sri Venkateswara College, University of Delhi, Delhi
</p>
<p>Sangeeta Sharma, PGT (Biology), Kendriya Vidyalaya, JNU, New Delhi
</p>
<p>Savithri Singh, Principal, Acharya Narendra Dev College, University of Delhi, Delhi
</p>
<p>Shanti Chandrashekaran, Principal Scientist, Division of Genetics, I.A.R.I., New Delhi
</p>
<p>Shardendu, Reader, Department of Botany, Science College, Patna University, Patna
</p>
<p>Simminder K. Thukral, Assistant Professor, NIIT Institute of Information Technology, New Delhi
</p>
<p>Sunaina Sharma, Lecturer (Biology), Rajkiya Pratibha Vikas Vidyalaya, Dwarka, New Delhi
</p>
<p>T.R. Rao, Professor (Retd.) School of Enviornmental Studies, University of Delhi, Delhi
</p>
<p>V.K. Kakaria, Reader, Regional Institute of Education, Bhopal
</p>
<p>V.V. Anand, Reader, Regional Institute of Education, Mysore
</p>
<p>MEMBER-COORDINATOR
</p>
<p>B.K. Tripathi, Reader, Department of Education in Science and Mathematics, NCERT, New Delhi
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>VIII
</p>
<p>National Council of Educational Research and Training (NCERT) gratefully acknowledges
</p>
<p>the valuable contribution of  K.R. Shivanna, Professor (Retd.), Department of Botany,
</p>
<p>University of Delhi, Delhi; S.K. Saidapur, Professor, Department of Zoology, Karnataka
</p>
<p>University Dharwad; Vani Brahmachari, Professor, Ambedkar Centre  for Biomedical
</p>
<p>Research, University of Delhi, Delhi; A.N. Lahiri Majumdar, Professor, Bose Institute, Kolkata;
</p>
<p>Anil Tripathi, Professor,  Department of Biotechnology, Banaras Hindu University, Varanasi;
</p>
<p>J.L. Jain, Senior Physician, WUS Health Centre, University of Delhi, Delhi, in the development
</p>
<p>of the Biology textbook for Class XII. NCERT is also grateful to K.R. Shivanna and
</p>
<p>T.Subramanyam, IIT, Kanpur for some of the photographs used in the book.
</p>
<p>NCERT sincerely acknowledges the contributions of the members who participated in the
</p>
<p>review of the manuscripts – A.S. Dixit, Reader, Department of Zoology, North-Eastern Hill
</p>
<p>University, Shillong; S.L. Varte, Lecturer, Department of Education in Science and Mathematics,
</p>
<p>NCERT, New Delhi; Sushma Jairath, Reader, Department of  Women’s Education, NCERT,
</p>
<p>New Delhi; Mona Yadav, Lecturer, Department of  Women’s Education, NCERT, New Delhi;
</p>
<p>Poonam A. Kant, Reader (Zoology), Acharya Narendra Dev College, New Delhi; Mrs. Suvarna
</p>
<p>Fonseca è Antao, Gr. I Teacher (Biology), Carmel Higher Secondary School, Nuvem, Goa;
</p>
<p>Rashmi Mishra, PGT (Biology), Carmel Convent Senior Secondary School, BHEL, Bhopal;
</p>
<p>Ishwant Kaur, PGT (Biology), D.M. School, RIE, Bhopal; A.K. Singh, PGT (Biology), Kendriya
</p>
<p>Vidyalaya, Cantt, Varanasi; R.P. Singh, Lecturer (Biology), Rajkiya Pratibha Vikash Vidyalaya,
</p>
<p>Kishan ganj, Delhi; M.K. Tiwari, PGT (Biology), Kendriya Vidyalaya, Mandsaur, Madhya Pradesh;
</p>
<p>A.K. Ganguly, PGT (Biology), Jawahar Navodaya Vidyalaya, Roshnabad, Haridwar; Chaitali
</p>
<p>Dixit, PGT (Biology), St. Anthony’s Higher Secondary School (Don Bosco), Shillong and Abhishek
</p>
<p>Chari, Acharya Narendra Dev College, New Delhi.
</p>
<p>The Council is highly thankful to Hukum Singh, Professor and Head, Department of
</p>
<p>Education in Science and Mathematics, NCERT for his valuable support throughout the
</p>
<p>making of this book.
</p>
<p>The contributions of Deepak Kapoor, Incharge, Computer Station; Seema Mehmi and
</p>
<p>Arvind Sharma, DTP operators; Deepti Sharma, Copy Editor; Rachna Dogra and Abhimanu
</p>
<p>Mohanty, Proof Readers and APC office and administrative staff of Department of Education
</p>
<p>in Science and Mathematics, NCERT also acknowledged.
</p>
<p>The efforts of the Publication Department, NCERT, in bringing out this publication are
</p>
<p>highly appreciated.
</p>
<p>ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>IX
</p>
<p>CONTENTS
</p>
<p>FOREWORD iii
</p>
<p>PREFACE vii
</p>
<p>UNIT VI
</p>
<p>REPRODUCTION 1-66
</p>
<p>Chapter 1  : Reproduction in Organisms 3
</p>
<p>Chapter 2  : Sexual Reproduction in Flowering Plants 19
</p>
<p>Chapter 3  : Human Reproduction 42
</p>
<p>Chapter 4  : Reproductive Health 57
</p>
<p>UNIT VII
</p>
<p>GENETICS AND EVOLUTION 67-142
</p>
<p>Chapter 5  : Principles of Inheritance and Variation 69
</p>
<p>Chapter 6  : Molecular Basis of Inheritance 95
</p>
<p>Chapter 7  : Evolution 126
</p>
<p>UNIT VIII
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY IN HUMAN WELFARE 143-190
</p>
<p>Chapter 8  : Human Health and Disease 145
</p>
<p>Chapter 9  : Strategies for Enhancement in 165
   Food Production
</p>
<p>Chapter 10  : Microbes in Human Welfare 179
</p>
<p>UNIT IX
</p>
<p>BIOTECHNOLOGY 191-216
</p>
<p>Chapter 11 : Biotechnology : Principles and Processes 193
</p>
<p>Chapter 12 : Biotechnology and its Applications 207
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>X
</p>
<p>UNIT X
</p>
<p>ECOLOGY 217-286
</p>
<p>Chapter 13 :  Organisms and Populations 219
</p>
<p>Chapter 14 :  Ecosystem 241
</p>
<p>Chapter 15 :  Biodiversity and Conservation 258
</p>
<p>Chapter 16 :  Environmental Issues 270
</p>
<p>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL 287–290
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="acroform"><ol/>
</div>
</body></html>