<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
<meta name="date" content="2015-04-10T04:15:18Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:PDFVersion" content="1.7"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:title" content="Reproductive Health.pmd"/>
<meta name="xmp:CreatorTool" content="PageMaker 7.0"/>
<meta name="access_permission:modify_annotations" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_print_degraded" content="true"/>
<meta name="dc:creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="dcterms:created" content="2014-06-05T06:28:30Z"/>
<meta name="Last-Modified" content="2015-04-10T04:15:18Z"/>
<meta name="dcterms:modified" content="2015-04-10T04:15:18Z"/>
<meta name="dc:format" content="application/pdf; version=1.7"/>
<meta name="dc:format" content="application/pdf; version=&quot;1.7 Adobe Extension Level 8&quot;"/>
<meta name="xmpMM:DocumentID" content="1bf78129-eed6-11e3-0000-78057e9a8840"/>
<meta name="Last-Save-Date" content="2015-04-10T04:15:18Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:creator_tool" content="PageMaker 7.0"/>
<meta name="access_permission:fill_in_form" content="true"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:modified" content="2015-04-10T04:15:18Z"/>
<meta name="meta:save-date" content="2015-04-10T04:15:18Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:encrypted" content="false"/>
<meta name="dc:title" content="Reproductive Health.pmd"/>
<meta name="modified" content="2015-04-10T04:15:18Z"/>
<meta name="Content-Length" content="675288"/>
<meta name="Content-Type" content="application/pdf"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="X-Parsed-By" content="org.apache.tika.parser.DefaultParser"/>
<meta name="X-Parsed-By" content="org.apache.tika.parser.pdf.PDFParser"/>
<meta name="creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="meta:author" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="meta:creation-date" content="2014-06-05T06:28:30Z"/>
<meta name="created" content="Thu Jun 05 11:58:30 IST 2014"/>
<meta name="pdf:PDFExtensionVersion" content="1.7 Adobe Extension Level 8"/>
<meta name="access_permission:extract_for_accessibility" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:assemble_document" content="true"/>
<meta name="xmpTPg:NPages" content="10"/>
<meta name="Creation-Date" content="2014-06-05T06:28:30Z"/>
<meta name="resourceName" content="lebo104.pdf"/>
<meta name="access_permission:extract_content" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_print" content="true"/>
<meta name="Author" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="producer" content="GPL Ghostscript 8.61"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_modify" content="true"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:producer" content="GPL Ghostscript 8.61"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:created" content="2014-06-05T06:28:30Z"/>
<title>Reproductive Health.pmd</title>
</head>
<body><div class="page"><p/>
<p>You have learnt about human reproductive system and its
functions in Chapter 3. Now, let’s discuss a closely related
topic – reproductive health. What do we understand by
this term?  The term simply refers to healthy reproductive
organs with normal functions. However, it has a broader
perspective and includes the emotional and social aspects
of reproduction also. According to the World Health
Organisation (WHO), reproductive health means a total
well-being in all aspects of reproduction, i.e., physical,
emotional, behavioural and social. Therefore, a society with
people having physically and functionally normal
reproductive organs and normal emotional and behavioural
interactions among them in all sex-related aspects might
be called reproductively healthy. Why is it significant to
maintain reproductive health and what are the methods
taken up to achieve it? Let us examine them.
</p>
<p>4.1 REPRODUCTIVE HEALTH – PROBLEMS AND
STRATEGIES
</p>
<p>India was amongst the first countries in the world to
</p>
<p>initiate action plans and programmes at a national level
</p>
<p>to attain total reproductive health as a social goal.
</p>
<p>These programmes called ‘family planning’ were
</p>
<p>initiated in 1951 and were periodically assessed over
</p>
<p>the past decades. Improved programmes covering wider
</p>
<p>CHAPTER 4
</p>
<p>REPRODUCTIVE HEALTH
</p>
<p>4.1 Reproductive Health –
</p>
<p>Problems and Strategies
</p>
<p>4.2 Population Explosion
</p>
<p>and Birth Control
</p>
<p>4.3 Medical Termination of
</p>
<p>Pregnancy
</p>
<p>4.4 Sexually Transmitted
</p>
<p>Diseases
</p>
<p>4.5 Infertility
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>58
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>reproduction-related areas are currently in operation under the
</p>
<p>popular name ‘Reproductive and Child Health Care (RCH) programmes’.
</p>
<p>Creating awareness among people about various reproduction related
</p>
<p>aspects and providing facilities and support for building up a
</p>
<p>reproductively healthy society are the major tasks under these
</p>
<p>programmes.
</p>
<p>With the help of audio-visual and the print-media governmental and
</p>
<p>non-governmental agencies have taken various steps to create awareness
</p>
<p>among the people about reproduction-related aspects. Parents, other
</p>
<p>close relatives, teachers and friends, also have a major role in the
</p>
<p>dissemination of the above information. Introduction of sex education
</p>
<p>in schools should also be encouraged to provide right information to
</p>
<p>the young so as to discourage children from believing in myths and
</p>
<p>having misconceptions about sex-related aspects. Proper information
</p>
<p>about reproductive organs, adolescence and related changes, safe and
</p>
<p>hygienic sexual practices, sexually transmitted diseases (STD), AIDS,
</p>
<p>etc., would help people, especially those in the adolescent age group to
</p>
<p>lead a reproductively healthy life. Educating people, especially fertile
</p>
<p>couples and those in marriageable age group, about available birth
</p>
<p>control options, care of pregnant mothers, post-natal care of the mother
</p>
<p>and child, importance of breast feeding, equal opportunities for the male
</p>
<p>and the female child, etc., would address the importance of bringing up
</p>
<p>socially conscious healthy families of desired size. Awareness of problems
</p>
<p>due to uncontrolled population growth, social evils like sex-abuse and
</p>
<p>sex-related crimes, etc., need to be created to enable people to think
</p>
<p>and take up necessary steps to prevent them and thereby build up a
</p>
<p>socially responsible and healthy society.
</p>
<p>Successful implementation of various action plans to attain
</p>
<p>reproductive health requires strong infrastructural facilities, professional
</p>
<p>expertise and material support. These are essential to provide medical
</p>
<p>assistance and care to people in reproduction-related problems like
</p>
<p>pregnancy, delivery, STDs, abortions, contraception, menstrual problems,
</p>
<p>infertility, etc. Implementation of better techniques and new strategies
</p>
<p>from time to time are also required to provide more efficient care and
</p>
<p>assistance to people. Statutory ban on amniocentesis (a foetal sex
</p>
<p>determination test based on the chromosomal pattern in the amniotic
</p>
<p>fluid surrounding the developing embryo) for sex-determination to legally
</p>
<p>check increasing female foeticides, massive child immunisation, etc., are
</p>
<p>some programmes that merit mention in this connection.
</p>
<p>Research on various reproduction-related areas are encouraged and
</p>
<p>supported by governmental and non-governmental agencies to find out
</p>
<p>new methods and/or to improve upon the existing ones. Do you know
</p>
<p>that ‘Saheli’–a new oral contraceptive for the females–was developed
</p>
<p>by scientists at Central Drug Research Institute (CDRI) in Lucknow, India?
</p>
<p>Better awareness about sex related matters, increased number of medically
</p>
<p>assisted deliveries and better post-natal care leading to decreased maternal
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>59
</p>
<p>REPRODUCTIVE HEALTH
</p>
<p>and infant mortality rates, increased number of couples with small
</p>
<p>families, better detection and cure of STDs and overall increased medical
</p>
<p>facilities for all sex-related problems, etc. all indicate improved reproductive
</p>
<p>health of the society.
</p>
<p>4.2 POPULATION EXPLOSION AND BIRTH CONTROL
</p>
<p>In the last century an all-round development in various fields significantly
</p>
<p>improved the quality of life of the people. However, increased health facilities
</p>
<p>along with better living conditions had an explosive impact on the growth
</p>
<p>of population. The world population which was around 2 billion
</p>
<p>(2000 million) in 1900 rocketed to about 6 billions  by 2000. A similar
</p>
<p>trend was observed in India too. Our population which was approximately
</p>
<p>350 million at the time of our independence reached close to the billion
</p>
<p>mark by 2000 and crossed 1 billion in May 2000. That means, every
</p>
<p>sixth person in the world is an Indian. A rapid decline in death rate,
</p>
<p>maternal mortality rate (MMR) and infant mortality rate (IMR) as
</p>
<p>well as an increase in number of people in reproducible age are probable
</p>
<p>reasons for this. Through our RCH programmes, though we could bring
</p>
<p>down the population growth rate, it was only marginal. According to the
</p>
<p>2001 census report, the population growth rate was still around  1.7 per
</p>
<p>cent, i.e., 17/1000/year, a rate at which our population could double in
</p>
<p>33 years. Such an alarming growth rate could lead to an absolute scarcity
</p>
<p>of even the basic requirements, i.e., food, shelter and clothing, in spite of
</p>
<p>significant progress made in those areas. Therefore, the government was
</p>
<p>forced to take up serious measures to check this population growth rate.
</p>
<p>The most important step to overcome this problem is to motivate smaller
</p>
<p>families by using various contraceptive methods. You might have seen
</p>
<p>advertisements in the media as well as posters/bills, etc., showing a happy
</p>
<p>couple with two children with a slogan Hum Do Hamare Do (we two, our
</p>
<p>two). Many couples, mostly the young, urban, working ones have even
</p>
<p>adopted an ‘one child norm’. Statutory raising of marriageable age of the
</p>
<p>female to 18 years and that of males to 21 years, and incentives given to
</p>
<p>couples with small families are two of the other measures taken to tackle
</p>
<p>this problem. Let us describe some of the commonly used contraceptive
</p>
<p>methods, which help prevent unwanted pregnancies.
</p>
<p>An ideal contraceptive should be user-friendly, easily available,
</p>
<p>effective and reversible with no or least side-effects. It also should in no
</p>
<p>way interfere with the sexual drive, desire and/or the sexual act of the
</p>
<p>user. A wide range of contraceptive methods are presently available which
</p>
<p>could be broadly grouped into the following categories, namely
</p>
<p>Natural/Traditional, Barrier, IUDs, Oral contraceptives, Injectables,
</p>
<p>Implants and Surgical methods.
</p>
<p>Natural methods work on the principle of avoiding chances of ovum
</p>
<p>and sperms meeting. Periodic abstinence is one such method in which
</p>
<p>the couples avoid or abstain from coitus from day 10 to 17 of the menstrual
</p>
<p>cycle when ovulation could be expected. As chances of fertilisation are
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>60
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>Figure 4.2. Copper T (CuT)
</p>
<p>very high during this period, it is called the fertile period. Therefore, by
</p>
<p>abstaining from coitus during this period, conception could be prevented.
</p>
<p>Withdrawal or coitus interruptus is another method in which the male
</p>
<p>partner withdraws his penis from the vagina just before ejaculation so as
</p>
<p>to avoid insemination. Lactational amenorrhea (absence of
</p>
<p>menstruation) method is based on the fact that ovulation
</p>
<p>and therefore the cycle do not occur during the period of
</p>
<p>intense lactation following parturition. Therefore, as long
</p>
<p>as the mother breast-feeds the child fully, chances of
</p>
<p>conception are almost nil. However, this method has been
</p>
<p>reported to be effective only upto a maximum period of six
</p>
<p>months following parturition. As no medicines or devices
</p>
<p>are used in these methods, side effects are almost nil.
</p>
<p>Chances of failure, though, of this method are also high.
</p>
<p>In barrier methods, ovum and sperms are prevented
</p>
<p>from physically meeting with the help of barriers. Such
</p>
<p>methods  are available for both males and females.
</p>
<p>Condoms (Figure 4.1 a, b) are barriers made of thin rubber/
</p>
<p>latex sheath that are used to cover the penis in the male or
</p>
<p>vagina and cervix in the female, just before coitus so that
</p>
<p>the ejaculated semen would not enter into the female
</p>
<p>reproductive tract. This can prevent conception. ‘Nirodh’ is
</p>
<p>a popular brand of condom for the male. Use of condoms
</p>
<p>has increased in recent years due to its additional benefit of
</p>
<p>protecting the user from contracting STDs and AIDS. Both
</p>
<p>the male and the female condoms are disposable, can be
</p>
<p>self-inserted and thereby gives privacy to the user.
</p>
<p>Diaphragms, cervical caps and vaults are also barriers
</p>
<p>made of rubber that are inserted into the female reproductive
</p>
<p>tract to cover the cervix during coitus. They prevent
</p>
<p>conception by blocking the entry of sperms through the
</p>
<p>cervix. They are reusable. Spermicidal creams, jellies and
</p>
<p>foams are usually used alongwith these barriers to increase
</p>
<p>their contraceptive efficiency.
</p>
<p>Another effective and popular method is the use of Intra
</p>
<p>Uterine Devices (IUDs). These devices are inserted by
</p>
<p>doctors or expert nurses in the uterus through vagina.
</p>
<p>These Intra Uterine Devices are presently available as the
</p>
<p>non-medicated IUDs (e.g., Lippes loop), copper releasing
</p>
<p>IUDs (CuT, Cu7, Multiload 375) and the hormone releasing IUDs
</p>
<p>(Progestasert, LNG-20) (Figure 4.2). IUDs increase phagocytosis of sperms
</p>
<p>within the uterus and the Cu ions released suppress sperm motility
</p>
<p>and the fertilising capacity of sperms. The hormone releasing IUDs,
</p>
<p>in addition, make the uterus unsuitable for implantation and the
</p>
<p>cervix hostile to the sperms. IUDs are ideal contraceptives for the females
</p>
<p>Figure 4.1(b) Condom for female
</p>
<p>Figure 4.1(a) Condom for male
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>61
</p>
<p>REPRODUCTIVE HEALTH
</p>
<p>who want to delay pregnancy and/or space children. It is
</p>
<p>one of most widely accepted methods of contraception in
</p>
<p>India.
</p>
<p>Oral administration of small doses of either progestogens
</p>
<p>or progestogen–estrogen combinations is another
</p>
<p>contraceptive method used by the females. They are used
</p>
<p>in the form of tablets and hence are popularly called the
</p>
<p>pills. Pills have to be taken daily for a period of 21 days
</p>
<p>starting preferably within the first five days of menstrual
</p>
<p>cycle. After a gap of 7 days (during which menstruation
</p>
<p>occurs) it has to be repeated in the same pattern till the
</p>
<p>female desires to prevent conception. They inhibit ovulation
</p>
<p>and implantation as well as alter the quality of cervical mucus to prevent/
</p>
<p>retard entry of sperms. Pills are very effective with lesser side effects and
</p>
<p>are well accepted by the females. Saheli –the new oral contraceptive for
</p>
<p>the females contains a non-steroidal preparation. It is a ‘once a week’ pill
</p>
<p>with very few side effects and high contraceptive value.
</p>
<p>Progestogens alone or in combination with estrogen can also be used
</p>
<p>by females as injections or implants under the skin (Figure 4.3). Their
</p>
<p>mode of action is similar to that of pills and their effective periods are
</p>
<p>much longer. Administration of progestogens or progestogen-estrogen
</p>
<p>combinations or IUDs within 72 hours of coitus have been found to be
</p>
<p>very effective as emergency contraceptives as they could be used to avoid
</p>
<p>possible pregnancy due to rape or casual unprotected intercourse.
</p>
<p>Surgical methods, also called sterilisation, are generally advised for
</p>
<p>the male/female partner as a terminal method to prevent any more
</p>
<p>pregnancies. Surgical intervention blocks gamete transport and thereby
</p>
<p>prevent conception. Sterilisation procedure in the male is called ‘vasectomy’
</p>
<p>Figure 4.3 Implants
</p>
<p>Figure 4.4a Vasectomy
Figure 4.4 (b) Tubectomy
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>62
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>and that in the female, ‘tubectomy’. In vasectomy, a small part of the vas
</p>
<p>deferens is removed or tied up through a small incision on the scrotum
</p>
<p>(Figure 4.4a) whereas in tubectomy, a small part of the fallopian tube is
</p>
<p>removed (Figure 4.4b) or tied up through a small incision in the abdomen
</p>
<p>or through vagina. These techniques are highly effective but their
</p>
<p>reversibility is very poor.
</p>
<p>It needs to be emphasised that the selection of a suitable contraceptive
</p>
<p>method and its use should always be undertaken in consultation with
</p>
<p>qualified medical professionals. One must also remember that
</p>
<p>contraceptives are not regular requirements for the maintenance of
</p>
<p>reproductive health. In fact, they are practiced against a natural
</p>
<p>reproductive event, i.e., conception/pregnancy. One is forced to use these
</p>
<p>methods either to prevent pregnancy or to delay or space pregnancy due
</p>
<p>to personal reasons. No doubt, the widespread use of these methods have
</p>
<p>a significant role in checking uncontrolled growth of population. However,
</p>
<p>their possible ill-effects like nausea, abdominal pain, breakthrough
</p>
<p>bleeding, irregular menstrual bleeding or even breast cancer, though not
</p>
<p>very significant, should not be totally ignored.
</p>
<p>4.3 MEDICAL TERMINATION OF PREGNANCY (MTP)
</p>
<p>Intentional or voluntary termination of pregnancy before full term is called
</p>
<p>medical termination of pregnancy (MTP) or induced abortion. Nearly
</p>
<p>45 to 50 million MTPs are performed in a year all over the world which
</p>
<p>accounts to 1/5th of the total number of conceived pregnancies in a year.
</p>
<p>Obviously, MTP has a significant role in decreasing the population though
</p>
<p>it is not meant for that purpose. Whether to accept / legalise MTP or not is
</p>
<p>being debated upon in many countries due to emotional, ethical, religious
</p>
<p>and social issues involved in it. Government of India legalised MTP in
</p>
<p>1971 with some strict conditions to avoid its misuse. Such restrictions
</p>
<p>are all the more important to check indiscriminate and illegal female
</p>
<p>foeticides which are reported to be high in India.
</p>
<p>Why MTP? Obviously the answer is –to get rid of unwanted
</p>
<p>pregnancies either due to casual unprotected intercourse or failure of the
</p>
<p>contraceptive used during coitus or rapes. MTPs are also essential in
</p>
<p>certain cases where continuation of the pregnancy could be harmful or
</p>
<p>even fatal either to the mother or to the foetus or both.
</p>
<p>MTPs are considered relatively safe during the first trimester, i.e., upto
</p>
<p>12 weeks of pregnancy. Second trimester abortions are much more riskier.
</p>
<p>One disturbing trend observed is that a majority of the MTPs are performed
</p>
<p>illegally by unqualified quacks which are not only unsafe but could be
</p>
<p>fatal too. Another dangerous trend is the misuse of amniocentesis to
</p>
<p>determine the sex of the unborn child.  Frequently, if the foetus is found
</p>
<p>to be female, it is followed by MTP- this is totally against what is legal.
</p>
<p>Such practices should be avoided because these are dangerous both for
</p>
<p>the young mother and the foetus. Effective counselling on the need to
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>63
</p>
<p>REPRODUCTIVE HEALTH
</p>
<p>avoid unprotected coitus and the risk factors involved in illegal abortions
</p>
<p>as well as providing more health care facilities could reverse the mentioned
</p>
<p>unhealthy trend.
</p>
<p>4.4 SEXUALLY TRANSMITTED DISEASES (STDS)
</p>
<p>Diseases or infections which are transmitted through sexual intercourse
</p>
<p>are collectively called sexually transmitted diseases (STD) or venereal
</p>
<p>diseases (VD) or reproductive tract infections (RTI). Gonorrhoea, syphilis,
</p>
<p>genital herpes, chlamydiasis, genital warts, trichomoniasis, hepatitis-B
</p>
<p>and of course, the most discussed infection in the recent years, HIV leading
</p>
<p>to AIDS are some of the common STDs. Among these, HIV infection is
</p>
<p>most dangerous and is discussed in detail in Chapter 8.
</p>
<p>Some of these infections like hepatitis–B and HIV can also be
</p>
<p>transmitted by sharing of injection needles, surgical instruments, etc.,
</p>
<p>with infected persons, transfusion of blood, or from an infected mother to
</p>
<p>the foetus too. Except for hepatitis-B, genital herpes and HIV infections,
</p>
<p>other diseases are completely curable if detected early and treated
</p>
<p>properly. Early symptoms of most of these are minor and include itching,
</p>
<p>fluid discharge, slight pain, swellings, etc., in the genital region. Infected
</p>
<p>females may often be asymptomatic and hence, may remain undetected
</p>
<p>for long. Absence or less significant symptoms in the early stages of
</p>
<p>infection and the social stigma attached to the STDs, deter the infected
</p>
<p>persons from going for timely detection and proper treatment. This could
</p>
<p>lead to complications later, which include pelvic inflammatory diseases
</p>
<p>(PID), abortions, still births, ectopic pregnancies, infertility or even cancer
</p>
<p>of the reproductive tract. STDs are a major threat to a healthy society.
</p>
<p>Therefore, prevention or early detection and cure of these diseases are
</p>
<p>given prime consideration under the reproductive health-care
</p>
<p>programmes. Though all persons are vulnerable to these infections, their
</p>
<p>incidences are reported to be very high among persons in the age group
</p>
<p>of 15-24 years – the age group to which you also belong. There is no
</p>
<p>reason to panic because prevention is possible. One could be free of these
</p>
<p>infections by following the simple principles given below:
</p>
<p>(i) Avoid sex with unknown partners/multiple partners.
</p>
<p>(ii) Always use condoms during coitus.
</p>
<p>(iii) In case of doubt, one should go to a qualified doctor for early
</p>
<p>detection and get complete treatment if diagnosed with disease.
</p>
<p>4.5 INFERTILITY
</p>
<p>A discussion on reproductive health is incomplete without a mention of
</p>
<p>infertility. A large number of couples all over the world including India
</p>
<p>are infertile, i.e., they are unable to produce children inspite of unprotected
</p>
<p>sexual co-habitation. The reasons for this could be many–physical,
</p>
<p>congenital, diseases, drugs, immunological or even psychological.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>64
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>In India, often the female is blamed for the couple being childless, but
</p>
<p>more often than not, the problem lies in the male partner. Specialised
</p>
<p>health care units (infertility clinics, etc.) could help in diagnosis and
</p>
<p>corrective treatment of some of these disorders and enable these couples to
</p>
<p>have children. However, where such corrections are not possible, the couples
</p>
<p>could be assisted to have children through certain special techniques
</p>
<p>commonly known as assisted reproductive technologies (ART).
</p>
<p>In vitro fertilisation (IVF–fertilisation outside the body in almost
</p>
<p>similar conditions as that in the body) followed by embryo transfer (ET)
</p>
<p>is one of such methods. In this method, popularly known as test tube
</p>
<p>baby programme, ova from the wife/donor (female) and sperms from the
</p>
<p>husband/donor (male) are collected and are induced to form zygote under
</p>
<p>simulated conditions in the laboratory. The zygote or early embryos (with
</p>
<p>upto 8 blastomeres) could then be transferred into the fallopian tube
</p>
<p>(ZIFT–zygote intra fallopian transfer) and embryos with more than
</p>
<p>8 blastomeres, into the uterus (IUT – intra uterine transfer), to complete
</p>
<p>its further development. Embryos formed by in-vivo fertilisation (fusion
</p>
<p>of gametes within the female) also could be used for such transfer to assist
</p>
<p>those females who cannot conceive.
</p>
<p>Transfer of an ovum collected from a donor into the fallopian tube
</p>
<p>(GIFT – gamete intra fallopian transfer) of another female who cannot
</p>
<p>produce one, but can provide suitable environment for fertilisation and
</p>
<p>further development is another method attempted. Intra cytoplasmic
</p>
<p>sperm injection (ICSI) is another specialised procedure to form an embryo
</p>
<p>in the laboratory in which a sperm is directly injected into the ovum.
</p>
<p>Infertility cases either due to inability of the male partner to inseminate
</p>
<p>the female or due to very low sperm counts in the ejaculates, could be
</p>
<p>corrected by artificial insemination (AI) technique. In this technique,
</p>
<p>the semen collected either from the husband or a healthy donor is artificially
</p>
<p>introduced either into the vagina or into the uterus (IUI – intra-uterine
</p>
<p>insemination) of the female.
</p>
<p>Though options are many, all these techniques require extremely
</p>
<p>high precision handling by specialised professionals and expensive
</p>
<p>instrumentation. Therefore, these facilities are presently available only
</p>
<p>in very few centres in the country. Obviously their benefits is affordable
</p>
<p>to only a limited number of people.  Emotional, religious and social
</p>
<p>factors are also deterrents in the adoption of these methods.  Since the
</p>
<p>ultimate aim of all these procedures is to have children, in India we have
</p>
<p>so many orphaned and destitute children, who would probably not
</p>
<p>survive till maturity, unless taken care of. Our laws permit legal adoption
</p>
<p>and it is as yet, one of the best methods for couples looking for
</p>
<p>parenthood.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>65
</p>
<p>REPRODUCTIVE HEALTH
</p>
<p>SUMMARY
</p>
<p>Reproductive health refers to a total well-being in all aspects of
</p>
<p>reproduction, i.e., physical, emotional, behavioural and social. Our
</p>
<p>nation was the first nation in the world to initiate various action plans
</p>
<p>at national level towards attaining a reproductively healthy society.
</p>
<p>Counselling and creating awareness among people about
</p>
<p>reproductive organs, adolescence and associated changes, safe and
</p>
<p>hygienic sexual practices, sexually transmitted diseases (STDs)
</p>
<p>including AIDS, etc., is the primary step towards reproductive health.
</p>
<p>Providing medical facilities and care to the problems like menstrual
</p>
<p>irregularities, pregnancy related aspects, delivery, medical termination
</p>
<p>of pregnancy, STDs, birth control, infertility, post natal child and
</p>
<p>maternal management is another important aspect of the Reproductive
</p>
<p>and Child Health Care programmes.
</p>
<p>An overall improvement in reproductive health has taken place in
</p>
<p>our country as indicated by reduced maternal and infant mortality
</p>
<p>rates, early detection and cure of STDs, assistance to infertile couples,
</p>
<p>etc. Improved health facilities and better living conditions promoted an
</p>
<p>explosive growth of population. Such a growth necessitated intense
</p>
<p>propagation of contraceptive methods. Various contraceptive options
</p>
<p>are available now such as natural, traditional, barrier, IUDs, pills,
</p>
<p>injectables, implants and surgical methods. Though contraceptives are
</p>
<p>not regular requirements for reproductive health, one is forced to use
</p>
<p>them to avoid pregnancy or to delay or space pregnancy.
</p>
<p>Medical termination of pregnancy is legalised in our country.  MTP is
</p>
<p>generally performed to get rid of unwanted pregnancy due to rapes, casual
</p>
<p>relationship, etc., as also in cases when the continuation of pregnancy
</p>
<p>could be harmful or even fatal to either the mother, or the foetus or both.
</p>
<p>Diseases or infections transmitted through sexual intercourse are
</p>
<p>called Sexually Transmitted Diseases (STDs). Pelvic Inflammatory
</p>
<p>Diseases (PIDs), still birth, infertility are some of the complications of
</p>
<p>them.  Early detection facilitate better cure of these diseases.  Avoiding
</p>
<p>sexual intercourse with unknown/multiple partners, use of condoms
</p>
<p>during coitus are some of the simple precautions to avoid  contracting
</p>
<p>STDs.
</p>
<p>Inability to conceive or produce children even after 2 years of
</p>
<p>unprotected sexual cohabitation is called infertility. Various methods
</p>
<p>are now available to help such couples. In Vitro fertilisation followed by
</p>
<p>transfer of embryo into the female genital tract is one such method and
</p>
<p>is commonly known as the ‘Test Tube Baby’ Programme.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>66
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>EXERCISES
</p>
<p>1. What do you think is the significance of reproductive health in a society?
</p>
<p>2. Suggest the aspects of reproductive health which need to be given
special attention in the present scenario.
</p>
<p>3. Is sex education necessary in schools?  Why?
</p>
<p>4. Do you think that reproductive health in our country has improved in
the past 50 years?  If yes, mention some such areas of improvement.
</p>
<p>5. What are the suggested reasons for population explosion?
</p>
<p>6. Is the use of contraceptives justified?  Give reasons.
</p>
<p>7. Removal of gonads cannot be considered as a contraceptive option.  Why?
</p>
<p>8. Amniocentesis for sex determination is banned in our country. Is this
ban necessary? Comment.
</p>
<p>9. Suggest some methods to assist infertile couples to have children.
</p>
<p>10. What are the measures one has to take to prevent from contracting STDs?
</p>
<p>11. State True/False with explanation
</p>
<p>(a) Abortions could happen spontaneously too. (True/False)
</p>
<p>(b) Infertility is defined as the inability to produce a viable offspring
and is always due to abnormalities/defects in the female partner.
(True/False)
</p>
<p>(c) Complete lactation could help as a natural method of
contraception. (True/False)
</p>
<p>(d) Creating awareness about sex related aspects is an effective
method to improve reproductive health of the people. (True/False)
</p>
<p>12. Correct the following statements :
</p>
<p>(a) Surgical methods of contraception prevent gamete formation.
</p>
<p>(b) All sexually transmitted diseases are completely curable.
</p>
<p>(c) Oral pills are very popular contraceptives among the rural women.
</p>
<p>(d) In E. T. techniques, embryos are always transferred into the uterus.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="acroform"><ol/>
</div>
</body></html>