<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
<meta name="date" content="2015-04-10T04:11:29Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:PDFVersion" content="1.7"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:title" content="CHAPTER 9.pmd"/>
<meta name="xmp:CreatorTool" content="PageMaker 7.0"/>
<meta name="access_permission:modify_annotations" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_print_degraded" content="true"/>
<meta name="dc:creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="dcterms:created" content="2014-06-05T08:50:48Z"/>
<meta name="Last-Modified" content="2015-04-10T04:11:29Z"/>
<meta name="dcterms:modified" content="2015-04-10T04:11:29Z"/>
<meta name="dc:format" content="application/pdf; version=1.7"/>
<meta name="dc:format" content="application/pdf; version=&quot;1.7 Adobe Extension Level 8&quot;"/>
<meta name="xmpMM:DocumentID" content="fd02ea7e-eee9-11e3-0000-1efab9e93eac"/>
<meta name="Last-Save-Date" content="2015-04-10T04:11:29Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:creator_tool" content="PageMaker 7.0"/>
<meta name="access_permission:fill_in_form" content="true"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:modified" content="2015-04-10T04:11:29Z"/>
<meta name="meta:save-date" content="2015-04-10T04:11:29Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:encrypted" content="false"/>
<meta name="dc:title" content="CHAPTER 9.pmd"/>
<meta name="modified" content="2015-04-10T04:11:29Z"/>
<meta name="Content-Length" content="1729882"/>
<meta name="Content-Type" content="application/pdf"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="X-Parsed-By" content="org.apache.tika.parser.DefaultParser"/>
<meta name="X-Parsed-By" content="org.apache.tika.parser.pdf.PDFParser"/>
<meta name="creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="meta:author" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="meta:creation-date" content="2014-06-05T08:50:48Z"/>
<meta name="created" content="Thu Jun 05 14:20:48 IST 2014"/>
<meta name="pdf:PDFExtensionVersion" content="1.7 Adobe Extension Level 8"/>
<meta name="access_permission:extract_for_accessibility" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:assemble_document" content="true"/>
<meta name="xmpTPg:NPages" content="14"/>
<meta name="Creation-Date" content="2014-06-05T08:50:48Z"/>
<meta name="resourceName" content="lebo109.pdf"/>
<meta name="access_permission:extract_content" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_print" content="true"/>
<meta name="Author" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="producer" content="GPL Ghostscript 8.61"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_modify" content="true"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:producer" content="GPL Ghostscript 8.61"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:created" content="2014-06-05T08:50:48Z"/>
<title>CHAPTER 9.pmd</title>
</head>
<body><div class="page"><p/>
<p>With ever -increasing population of the world,
</p>
<p>enhancement of food production is a major necessity.
</p>
<p>Biological principles as applied to animal husbandry and
</p>
<p>plant breeding have a major role in our efforts to increase
</p>
<p>food production. Several new techniques like embryo
</p>
<p>transfer technology and tissue culture techniques are going
</p>
<p>to play a pivotal role in further enhancing food production.
</p>
<p>9.1 ANIMAL HUSBANDRY
</p>
<p>Animal husbandry is the agricultural practice of breeding
</p>
<p>and raising livestock. As such it is a vital skill for farmers
</p>
<p>and is as much science as it is art.  Animal husbandry
</p>
<p>deals with the care and breeding of livestock like buffaloes,
</p>
<p>cows, pigs, horses, cattle, sheep, camels, goats, etc., that
</p>
<p>are useful to humans. Extended, it includes poultry
</p>
<p>farming and fisheries. Fisheries include rearing, catching,
</p>
<p>selling, etc., of fish, molluscs (shell-fish) and crustaceans
</p>
<p>(prawns, crabs, etc.). Since time immemorial, animals like
</p>
<p>bees, silk-worm, prawns, crabs, fishes, birds, pigs, cattle,
</p>
<p>sheep and camels have been used by humans for products
</p>
<p>like milk, eggs, meat, wool, silk, honey, etc.
</p>
<p>It is estimated that more then 70 per cent of the world
</p>
<p>livestock population is in India and China.  However, it is
</p>
<p>CHAPTER 9
</p>
<p>STRATEGIES FOR ENHANCEMENT
</p>
<p>IN FOOD PRODUCTION
</p>
<p>9.1 Animal Husbandry
</p>
<p>9.2 Plant Breeding
</p>
<p>9.3 Single Cell Proteins
</p>
<p>9.4 Tissue Culture
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>166
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>surprising to note that the contribution to the world farm produce is only
</p>
<p>25 per cent, i.e., the productivity per unit is very low. Hence, in addition
</p>
<p>to conventional practices of animal breeding and care, newer technologies
</p>
<p>also have to be applied to achieve improvement in quality and productivity.
</p>
<p>9.1.1 Management of Farms and Farm Animals
</p>
<p>A professional approach to what have been traditional practices of farm
</p>
<p>management gives the much needed boost to our food production. Let us
</p>
<p>discuss some of the management procedures, employed in various animal
</p>
<p>farm systems.
</p>
<p>9.1.1.1 Dairy Farm Management
</p>
<p>Dairying is the management of animals for milk and its products for
</p>
<p>human consumption.  Can you list the animals that you would expect
</p>
<p>to find in a dairy? What are different kinds of products that can be
</p>
<p>made with milk from a dairy farm?  In dairy farm management, we deal
</p>
<p>with processes and systems that increase yield and improve quality of
</p>
<p>milk.  Milk yield is primarily dependent on the quality of breeds in the
</p>
<p>farm. Selection of good breeds having high yielding potential (under the
</p>
<p>climatic conditions of the area), combined with resistance to diseases is
</p>
<p>very important. For the yield potential to be realised the cattle have to be
</p>
<p>well looked after – they have to be housed well, should have adequate
</p>
<p>water and be maintained disease free. The feeding of cattle should be
</p>
<p>carried out in a scientific manner – with special emphasis on the quality
</p>
<p>and quantity of fodder.  Besides, stringent cleanliness and hygiene (both
</p>
<p>of the cattle and the handlers) are of paramount importance while milking,
</p>
<p>storage and transport of the milk and its products. Nowadays, of course,
</p>
<p>much of these processes have become mechanised, which reduces chance
</p>
<p>of direct contact of the produce with the handler. Ensuring these stringent
</p>
<p>measures would of course, require regular inspections, with proper record
</p>
<p>keeping. It would also help to identify and rectify the problems as early
</p>
<p>as possible. Regular visits by a veterinary doctor would be  mandatory.
</p>
<p>You would probably find it interesting if you were to prepare a
</p>
<p>questionnaire on diverse aspects of dairy keeping and then follow it up with
</p>
<p>a visit to a dairy farm in your locality and seek answers to the questions.
</p>
<p>9.1.1.2 Poultry Farm Management
</p>
<p>Poultry is the class of domesticated fowl (birds) used for food or for their
</p>
<p>eggs.  They typically include chicken and ducks, and sometimes turkey and
</p>
<p>geese.  The word poultry is often used to refer to the meat of only these birds,
</p>
<p>but in a more general sense it may refer to the meat of other birds too.
</p>
<p>As in dairy farming, selection of disease free and suitable breeds,
</p>
<p>proper and safe farm conditions, proper feed and water, and hygiene and
</p>
<p>health care are important components of poultry farm management.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>STRATEGIES FOR ENHANCEMENT IN FOOD PRODUCTION
</p>
<p>167
</p>
<p>You may have seen TV news or read newspaper–
</p>
<p>reports about the ‘bird flu virus’ which created a scare in
</p>
<p>the country and drastically affected egg and chicken
</p>
<p>consumption.  Find out more about it and discuss whether
</p>
<p>the panic reaction was justified. How can we prevent the
</p>
<p>spread of the flu in case some chicken are infected?
</p>
<p>9.1.2 Animal Breeding
</p>
<p>Breeding of animals is an important aspect of animal
</p>
<p>husbandry.  Animal breeding aims at increasing the yield
</p>
<p>of animals and improving the desirable qualities of the
</p>
<p>produce. For what kind of characters would we breed
</p>
<p>animals? Would the selection of characters differ with
</p>
<p>the choice of animals?
</p>
<p>What do we understand by the term ‘breed’?  A group
</p>
<p>of animals related by descent and similar in most characters
</p>
<p>like general appearance, features, size, configuration, etc.,
</p>
<p>are said to belong to a breed. Find out the names of some
</p>
<p>common breeds of cattle and poultry in the farms of your
</p>
<p>area.
</p>
<p>When breeding is between animals of the same breed it
</p>
<p>is called inbreeding, while crosses between different breeds
</p>
<p>are called outbreeding.
</p>
<p>Inbreeding : Inbreeding refers to the mating of more
</p>
<p>closely related individuals within the same breed for 4-
</p>
<p>6 generations. The breeding strategy is as follows – superior males and
</p>
<p>superior females of the same breed are identified and mated in pairs.
</p>
<p>The progeny obtained from such matings are evaluated and superior
</p>
<p>males and females among them are identified for further mating. A
</p>
<p>superior female, in the case of cattle, is the cow or buffalo that produces
</p>
<p>more milk per lactation. On the other hand, a superior male is the bull,
</p>
<p>which gives rise to superior progeny as compared to those of other
</p>
<p>males.
</p>
<p>Try to recollect the homozygous purelines developed by Mendel as
</p>
<p>discussed in Chapter 5. A similar strategy is used for developing purelines
</p>
<p>in cattle as was used in case of peas. Inbreeding increases homozygosity.
</p>
<p>Thus inbreeding is necessary if we want to evolve a pureline in any animal.
</p>
<p>Inbreeding exposes harmful recessive genes that are eliminated by selection.
</p>
<p>It also helps in accumulation of superior genes and elimination of less
</p>
<p>desirable genes. Therefore, this approach, where there is selection at each
</p>
<p>step, increases the productivity of inbred population. However, continued
</p>
<p>inbreeding, especially close inbreeding, usually reduces fertility and even
</p>
<p>productivity. This is called inbreeding depression.  Whenever this becomes
</p>
<p>a problem, selected animals of the breeding population should be mated
</p>
<p>Figure 9.1 Improved breed of
cattle and chickens
(a) Jersey (b) Leghorn
</p>
<p>(a)
</p>
<p>(b)
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>168
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>with unrelated superior animals of the same breed. This usually helps
</p>
<p>restore fertility and yield.
</p>
<p>Out-breeding : Out-breeding is the breeding of the unrelated animals,
</p>
<p>which may be between individuals of the same breed but having no
</p>
<p>common ancestors for 4-6 generations (out-crossing) or between
</p>
<p>different breeds (cross-breeding) or different species (inter-specific
</p>
<p>hybridisation).
</p>
<p>Out-crossing: This is the practice of mating of animals within the same
</p>
<p>breed, but having no common ancestors on either side of their pedigree
</p>
<p>up to 4-6 generations. The offspring of such a mating is known as an
</p>
<p>out-cross. It is the best breeding method for animals that are below
</p>
<p>average in productivity in milk production, growth rate in beef cattle,
</p>
<p>etc. A single outcross often helps to overcome inbreeding depression.
</p>
<p>Cross-breeding: In this method, superior males of one breed are mated
</p>
<p>with superior females of another breed. Cross-breeding allows the
</p>
<p>desirable qualities of two different breeds to be combined. The progeny
</p>
<p>hybrid animals may themselves be used for commercial production.
</p>
<p>Alternatively, they may be subjected to some form of inbreeding and
</p>
<p>selection to develop new stable breeds that may be superior to the existing
</p>
<p>breeds. Many new animal breeds have been developed by this approach.
</p>
<p>Hisardale is a new breed of sheep developed in Punjab by crossing
</p>
<p>Bikaneri ewes and Marino rams.
</p>
<p>Interspecific hybridisation: In this method, male and female animals
</p>
<p>of two different related species are mated. In some cases, the progeny
</p>
<p>may combine desirable features of both the parents, and may be of
</p>
<p>considerable economic value, e.g., the mule (Figure 9.2). Do you know
</p>
<p>what cross leads to the production of the mule?
</p>
<p>Controlled breeding experiments are carried out using artificial
</p>
<p>insemination.  The semen is collected from the male that
</p>
<p>is chosen as a parent and injected into the reproductive
</p>
<p>tract of the selected female by the breeder.  The semen
</p>
<p>may be used immediately or can be frozen and used at a
</p>
<p>later date. It can also be transported in a frozen form to
</p>
<p>where the female is housed. In this way desirable matings
</p>
<p>are carried. Artificial insemination helps us overcome
</p>
<p>several problems of normal matings.  Can you discuss
</p>
<p>and list some of them?
</p>
<p>Often, the success rate of crossing mature male and
</p>
<p>female animals is fairly low even though artificial
</p>
<p>insemination is carried out.  To improve chances of
</p>
<p>successful production of hybrids, other means are also used. Multiple
</p>
<p>Ovulation Embryo Transfer Technology (MOET) is one such
</p>
<p>programme for herd improvement.  In this method, a cow is administered
</p>
<p>hormones, with FSH-like activity, to induce follicular maturation and super
</p>
<p>ovulation – instead of one egg, which they normally yield per cycle, they
</p>
<p>Figure 9.2 Mule
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>STRATEGIES FOR ENHANCEMENT IN FOOD PRODUCTION
</p>
<p>169
</p>
<p>produce 6-8 eggs. The animal is either mated with an elite bull or
</p>
<p>artificially inseminated. The fertilised eggs at 8–32 cells stages, are
</p>
<p>recovered non-surgically and transferred to surrogate mothers. The genetic
</p>
<p>mother is available for another round of super ovulation. This technology
</p>
<p>has been demonstrated for cattle, sheep, rabbits, buffaloes, mares, etc.
</p>
<p>High milk-yielding breeds of females and high quality (lean meat with
</p>
<p>less lipid) meat-yielding bulls have been bred successfully to increase
</p>
<p>herd size in a short time.
</p>
<p>9.1.3 Bee-keeping
</p>
<p>Bee-keeping or apiculture is the maintenance of hives of honeybees for
</p>
<p>the production of honey. It has been an age-old cottage industry. Honey
</p>
<p>is a food of high nutritive value and also finds use in the indigenous
</p>
<p>systems of medicine.  Honeybee also produces beeswax, which finds many
</p>
<p>uses in industry, such as in the preparation of cosmetics and polishes of
</p>
<p>various kinds. The increased demand of honey has led to large-scale bee-
</p>
<p>keeping practices; it has become an established income generating
</p>
<p>industry, whether practiced on a small or on a large scale.
</p>
<p>Bee-keeping can be practiced in any area where there are sufficient
</p>
<p>bee pastures of some wild shrubs, fruit orchards and cultivated crops.
</p>
<p>There are several species of honeybees which can be reared. Of these, the
</p>
<p>most common species is Apis indica. Beehives can be kept in one’s
</p>
<p>courtyard, on the verandah of the house or even on the roof. Bee-keeping
</p>
<p>is not labour-intensive.
</p>
<p>Bee-keeping though relatively easy does require some specialised
</p>
<p>knowledge and there are several organisations that teach bee-keeping.
</p>
<p>The following points are important for successful bee-keeping:
</p>
<p>(i) Knowledge of the nature and habits of bees,
</p>
<p>(ii) Selection of suitable location for keeping the beehives,
</p>
<p>(iii) Catching and hiving of swarms (group of bees),
</p>
<p>(iv) Management of beehives during different seasons, and
</p>
<p>(v) Handling and collection of honey and of beeswax. Bees are the pollinators
</p>
<p>of many of our crop species (see chapter 2) such as sunflower, Brassica,
</p>
<p>apple and pear. Keeping beehives in crop fields during flowering period
</p>
<p>increases pollination efficiency and improves the yield–beneficial both
</p>
<p>from the point of view of crop yield and honey yield.
</p>
<p>9.1.4 Fisheries
</p>
<p>Fishery is an industry devoted to the catching, processing or selling of fish,
</p>
<p>shellfish or other aquatic animals. A large number of our population is
</p>
<p>dependent on fish, fish products and other aquatic animals such as prawn,
</p>
<p>crab, lobster, edible oyster, etc., for food. Some of the freshwater fishes which
</p>
<p>are very common include Catla, Rohu and common carp. Some of the marine
</p>
<p>fishes that are eaten include – Hilsa, Sardines, Mackerel and Pomfrets.
</p>
<p>Find out what fishes are commonly eaten in your area.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>170
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>Fisheries has an important place in Indian economy. It provides income
</p>
<p>and employment to millions of fishermen and farmers, particularly in the
</p>
<p>coastal states.  For many, it is the only source of their livelihood. In order
</p>
<p>to meet the increasing demands on fisheries, different techniques have
</p>
<p>been employed to increase production. For example, through aquaculture
</p>
<p>and pisciculture we have been able to increase the production of aquatic
</p>
<p>plants and animals, both fresh-water and marine. Find out the difference
</p>
<p>between pisciculture and aquaculture. This has led to the development
</p>
<p>and flourishing of the fishery industry, and it has brought a lot of income
</p>
<p>to the farmers in particular and the country in general. We now talk about
</p>
<p>‘Blue Revolution’ as being implemented along the same lines as ‘Green
</p>
<p>Revolution’.
</p>
<p>9.2 PLANT BREEDING
</p>
<p>Traditional farming can only yield a limited biomass, as food for humans
</p>
<p>and animals. Better management practices and increase in acreage can
</p>
<p>increase yield, but only to a limited extent. Plant breeding as a technology
</p>
<p>has helped increase yields to a very large extent. Who in India has not
</p>
<p>heard of Green Revolution which was responsible for our country to
</p>
<p>not merely meet the national requirements in food production but also
</p>
<p>helped us even to export it?  Green revolution was dependent to a large
</p>
<p>extent on plant breeding techniques for development of high-yielding and
</p>
<p>disease resistant varieties in wheat, rice, maize, etc.
</p>
<p>9.2.1 What is Plant Breeding?
</p>
<p>Plant breeding is the purposeful manipulation of plant species in order to
</p>
<p>create desired plant types that are better suited for cultivation, give better
</p>
<p>yields and are disease resistant. Conventional plant breeding has been
</p>
<p>practiced for thousands of years, since the beginning of human civilisation;
</p>
<p>recorded evidence of plant breeding dates back to 9,000-11,000 years ago.
</p>
<p>Many present-day crops are the result of domestication in ancient times.
</p>
<p>Today, all our major food crops are derived from domesticated varieties.
</p>
<p>Classical plant breeding involves crossing or hybridisation of pure lines,
</p>
<p>followed by artificial selection to produce plants with desirable traits of higher
</p>
<p>yield, nutrition and resistance to diseases. With advancements in genetics,
</p>
<p>molecular biology and tissue culture, plant breeding is now increasingly
</p>
<p>being carried out by using molecular genetic tools.
</p>
<p>If we were to list the traits or characters that the breeders have tried to
</p>
<p>incorporate into crop plants, the first we would list would be increased
</p>
<p>crop yield and improved quality.  Increased tolerance to environmental
</p>
<p>stresses (salinity, extreme temperatures, drought), resistance to pathogens
</p>
<p>(viruses, fungi and bacteria) and  increased tolerance to insect pests would
</p>
<p>be on our list too.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>STRATEGIES FOR ENHANCEMENT IN FOOD PRODUCTION
</p>
<p>171
</p>
<p>Plant breeding programmes are carried out in a systematic way
</p>
<p>worldwide–in government institutions and commercial companies.  The
</p>
<p>main steps in breeding a new genetic variety of a crop are –
</p>
<p>(i) Collection of variability: Genetic variability is the root of any
</p>
<p>breeding programme. In many crops pre-existing genetic variability
</p>
<p>is available from wild relatives of the crop. Collection and preservation
</p>
<p>of all the different wild varieties, species and  relatives of the cultivated
</p>
<p>species (followed by their evaluation for their characteristics) is a
</p>
<p>pre-requisite for effective exploitation of natural genes available in
</p>
<p>the populations. The entire collection (of plants/seeds) having all
</p>
<p>the diverse alleles for all genes in a given crop is called germplasm
</p>
<p>collection.
</p>
<p>(ii) Evaluation and selection of parents: The germplasm is evaluated
</p>
<p>so as to identify plants with desirable combination of characters.
</p>
<p>The selected plants are multiplied and used in the process of
</p>
<p>hybridisation. Purelines are created wherever desirable and possible.
</p>
<p>(iii) Cross hybridisation among the selected parents: The desired
</p>
<p>characters have very often to be combined from two different plants
</p>
<p>(parents), for example high protein quality of one parent may need
</p>
<p>to be combined with disease resistance from another parent. This is
</p>
<p>possible by cross hybridising the two parents to produce hybrids
</p>
<p>that  genetically combine the desired characters in one plant. This is
</p>
<p>a very time-consuming and tedious process since the pollen
</p>
<p>grains from the desirable plant chosen as male parent have to be
</p>
<p>collected and placed on the stigma of the flowers selected as female
</p>
<p>parent (In chapter 2 details on how to make crosses have been
</p>
<p>described).  Also, it is not necessary that the hybrids do combine the
</p>
<p>desirable characters; usually only one in few hundred to a thousand
</p>
<p>crosses shows the desirable combination.
</p>
<p>(iv) Selection and testing of superior recombinants: This step
</p>
<p>consists of selecting, among the progeny of the hybrids, those plants
</p>
<p>that have the desired character combination. The selection process is
</p>
<p>crucial to the success of the breeding objective and requires careful
</p>
<p>scientific evaluation of the progeny. This step yields plants that are
</p>
<p>superior to both of the parents (very often more than one superior
</p>
<p>progeny plant may become available). These are self-pollinated for
</p>
<p>several generations till they reach a state of uniformity (homozygosity),
</p>
<p>so that the characters will not segregate in the progeny.
</p>
<p>(v) Testing, release and commercialisation of new cultivars: The
</p>
<p>newly selected lines are evaluated for their yield and other agronomic
</p>
<p>traits of quality, disease resistance, etc. This evaluation is done by
</p>
<p>growing these in the research fields and recording their performance
</p>
<p>under ideal fertiliser application, irrigation, and other crop
</p>
<p>management practices. The evaluation in research fields is followed
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>172
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>by testing the materials in farmers’ fields, for at least three growing
</p>
<p>seasons at several locations in the country, representing all the
</p>
<p>agroclimatic zones where the crop is usually grown. The material is
</p>
<p>evaluated in comparison to the best available local crop cultivar – a
</p>
<p>check or reference cultivar.
</p>
<p>India is mainly an agricultural country. Agriculture accounts
</p>
<p>for approximately 33 per cent of India’s GDP and employs nearly
</p>
<p>62 per cent of the population. After India’s independence, one of the main
</p>
<p>challenges facing the country was that of producing enough food for the
</p>
<p>increasing population. As only limited land is fit for cultivation, India has
</p>
<p>to strive to increase yields per unit area from existing farm land. The
</p>
<p>development of several high yielding varieties of wheat and rice in the
</p>
<p>mid-1960s, as a result of various plant breeding techniques led to dramatic
</p>
<p>increase in food production in our country.  This phase is often referred
</p>
<p>to as the Green Revolution. Figure 9.3 represents some Indian hybrid
</p>
<p>crops of high yeilding varieties.
</p>
<p>(c)
</p>
<p>(b)(a)
</p>
<p>Figure 9.3 Some Indian hybrid crops: (a) Maize; (b) Wheat; (c) Garden peas
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>STRATEGIES FOR ENHANCEMENT IN FOOD PRODUCTION
</p>
<p>173
</p>
<p>Wheat and Rice: During the period 1960 to 2000, wheat production
</p>
<p>increased from 11 million tonnes to 75 million tonnes while rice production
</p>
<p>went up from 35 million tonnes to 89.5 million tonnes. This was due to the
</p>
<p>development of semi-dwarf varieties of wheat and rice. Nobel laureate
</p>
<p>Norman E. Borlaug, at International Centre for Wheat and Maize
</p>
<p>Improvement in Mexico, developed semi-dwarf wheat. In 1963, several
</p>
<p>varieties such as Sonalika and Kalyan Sona, which were high yielding and
</p>
<p>disease resistant, were introduced all over the wheat-growing belt of India.
</p>
<p>Semi-dwarf rice varieties were derived from IR-8, (developed at International
</p>
<p>Rice Research Institute (IRRI), Philippines) and Taichung Native-1 (from
</p>
<p>Taiwan). The derivatives were introduced in 1966. Later  better-yielding semi-
</p>
<p>dwarf varieties Jaya and Ratna were developed in India.
</p>
<p>Sugar cane: Saccharum barberi was originally grown in north India, but
</p>
<p>had poor sugar content and yield. Tropical canes grown in south India
</p>
<p>Saccharum officinarum had thicker stems and higher sugar content but
</p>
<p>did not grow well in north India. These two species were successfully
</p>
<p>crossed to get sugar cane varieties combining the desirable qualities of
</p>
<p>high yield, thick stems, high sugar and ability to grow in the sugar cane
</p>
<p>areas of north India.
</p>
<p>Millets:  Hybrid maize, jowar and bajra have been successfully developed
</p>
<p>in India. Hybrid breeding have led to the development of several high
</p>
<p>yielding varieties resistant to water stress.
</p>
<p>9.2.2 Plant Breeding for Disease Resistance
</p>
<p>A wide range of fungal, bacterial and viral pathogens, affect the yield of
</p>
<p>cultivated crop species, especially in tropical climates. Crop losses can
</p>
<p>often be significant, up to 20-30 per cent, or sometimes even total. In this
</p>
<p>situation, breeding and development of cultivars resistant to disease
</p>
<p>enhances food production. This also helps reduce the dependence on
</p>
<p>use of  fungicides and bacteriocides. Resistance of the host plant is the
</p>
<p>ability to prevent the pathogen from causing disease and is determined
</p>
<p>by the genetic constitution of the host plant. Before breeding is
</p>
<p>undertaken, it is important to know about the causative organism and
</p>
<p>the mode of transmission. Some of the diseases caused by fungi are rusts,
</p>
<p>e.g., brown rust of wheat, red rot of sugarcane and late blight of potato;
</p>
<p>by  bacteria – black rot of crucifers; and by viruses – tobacco mosaic,
</p>
<p>turnip mosaic, etc.
</p>
<p>Methods of breeding for disease resistance: Breeding is carried
</p>
<p>out by the conventional breeding techniques (described earlier) or by
</p>
<p>mutation breeding. The conventional method of breeding for disease
</p>
<p>resistance is that of hybridisation and selection. It’s steps are essentially
</p>
<p>identical to those for breeding for any other agronomic characters such
</p>
<p>as high yield. The various sequential steps are : screening germplasm
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>174
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>for resistance sources, hybridisation of selected parents, selection and
</p>
<p>evaluation of the hybrids and testing and release of new varieties.
</p>
<p>Some crop varieties bred by hybridisation and selection, for
</p>
<p>disease resistance to fungi, bacteria and viral diseases are released
</p>
<p>(Table 9.1).
</p>
<p>Table 9.1
</p>
<p>Crop Variety Resistance to diseases
</p>
<p>Wheat Himgiri Leaf and stripe rust, hill bunt
</p>
<p>Brassica Pusa swarnim White rust
</p>
<p>(Karan rai)
</p>
<p>Cauliflower Pusa Shubhra, Black rot and Curl
</p>
<p>Pusa Snowball K-1 blight black rot
</p>
<p>Cowpea Pusa Komal Bacterial blight
</p>
<p>Chilli Pusa Sadabahar Chilly mosaic virus,
</p>
<p>Tobacco mosaic virus
</p>
<p>and Leaf curl
</p>
<p>Conventional breeding is often constrained by the availability of limited
</p>
<p>number of disease resistance genes that are present and identified in various
</p>
<p>crop varieties or wild relatives.  Inducing mutations in plants through diverse
</p>
<p>means and then screening the plant materials for resistance sometimes
</p>
<p>leads to desirable genes being identified.  Plants having these desirable
</p>
<p>characters can then be either multiplied directly or can be used in breeding.
</p>
<p>Other breeding methods that are used are selection amongst somaclonal
</p>
<p>variants and genetic engineering.
</p>
<p>Mutation is the process by which genetic variations are created
</p>
<p>through changes in the base sequence within genes (see Chapter 5)
</p>
<p>resulting in the creation of a new character or trait not found in the parental
</p>
<p>type. It is possible to induce mutations artificially through use of chemicals
</p>
<p>or radiations (like gamma radiations), and selecting and using the plants
</p>
<p>that have the desirable character as a source in breeding – this process is
</p>
<p>called mutation breeding. In mung bean, resistance to yellow mosaic
</p>
<p>virus and powdery mildew were induced by mutations.
</p>
<p>Several wild relatives of different cultivated species of plants have been
</p>
<p>shown to have certain resistant characters but have very low yield.  Hence,
</p>
<p>there is a need to introduce the resistant genes into the high-yielding
</p>
<p>cultivated varieties. Resistance to yellow mosaic virus in bhindi
</p>
<p>(Abelmoschus esculentus) was transferred from a wild species and
</p>
<p>resulted in a new variety of A. esculentus called Parbhani kranti.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>STRATEGIES FOR ENHANCEMENT IN FOOD PRODUCTION
</p>
<p>175
</p>
<p>All the above examples involve sources of resistance genes that are in
</p>
<p>the same crop species, which has to be bred for disease resistance, or in a
</p>
<p>related wild species. Transfer of resistance genes is achieved by sexual
</p>
<p>hybridisation between the target and the source plant followed by
</p>
<p>selection.
</p>
<p>9.2.3 Plant Breeding for Developing Resistance
to Insect Pests
</p>
<p>Another major cause for large scale destruction of crop plant and crop
</p>
<p>produce is insect and pest infestation. Insect resistance in host crop plants
</p>
<p>may be due to morphological, biochemical or physiological characteristics.
</p>
<p>Hairy leaves in several plants are associated with resistance to insect pests,
</p>
<p>e.g, resistance to jassids in cotton and cereal leaf beetle in wheat. In wheat,
</p>
<p>solid stems lead to non-preference by the stem sawfly and smooth leaved
</p>
<p>and nectar-less cotton varieties do not attract bollworms. High aspartic
</p>
<p>acid, low nitrogen and sugar content in maize leads to resistance to maize
</p>
<p>stem borers.
</p>
<p>Breeding methods for insect pest resistance involve the same steps as
</p>
<p>those for any other agronomic trait such as yield or quality and are as
</p>
<p>discussed earlier. Sources of resistance genes may be  cultivated varieties,
</p>
<p>germplasm collections of the crop or wild relatives.
</p>
<p>Some released crop varieties bred by hybridisation and selection, for
</p>
<p>insect pest resistance are given in Table 9.2.
</p>
<p>Table 9.2
</p>
<p>Crop Variety Insect Pests
</p>
<p>Brassica Pusa Gaurav Aphids
</p>
<p>(rapeseed mustard)
</p>
<p>Flat bean Pusa Sem 2, Jassids, aphids and
</p>
<p>Pusa Sem 3 fruit borer
</p>
<p>Okra (Bhindi) Pusa Sawani Shoot and Fruit borer
</p>
<p>Pusa A-4
</p>
<p>9.2.4 Plant Breeding for Improved Food Quality
</p>
<p>More than 840 million people in the world do not have adequate food to
</p>
<p>meet their daily food and nutritional requirements. A far greater number–
</p>
<p>three billion people – suffer from micronutrient, protein and vitamin
</p>
<p>deficiencies or ‘hidden hunger’ because they cannot afford to buy enough
</p>
<p>fruits, vegetables, legumes, fish and meat. Diets lacking essential
</p>
<p>micronutrients – particularly  iron, vitamin A, iodine and zinc – increase
</p>
<p>the risk for disease, reduce lifespan and reduce mental abilities.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>176
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>Biofortification – breeding crops with higher levels of vitamins and
</p>
<p>minerals, or higher protein and healthier fats – is the most practical
</p>
<p>means to improve public health.
</p>
<p>Breeding for improved nutritional quality is undertaken with the
</p>
<p>objectives of improving –
</p>
<p>(i) Protein content and quality;
</p>
<p>(ii) Oil content and quality;
</p>
<p>(iii) Vitamin content; and
</p>
<p>(iv) Micronutrient and mineral content.
</p>
<p>In 2000, maize hybrids that had twice the amount of the amino acids,
</p>
<p>lysine and tryptophan, compared to existing maize hybrids were
</p>
<p>developed. Wheat variety, Atlas 66, having a high protein content, has
</p>
<p>been used as a donor for improving cultivated wheat.  It has been possible
</p>
<p>to develop an iron-fortified rice variety containing over five times as much
</p>
<p>iron as in commonly consumed varieties.
</p>
<p>The Indian Agricultural Research Institute, New Delhi has also released
</p>
<p>several vegetable crops that are rich in vitamins and minerals, e.g., vitamin
</p>
<p>A enriched carrots, spinach, pumpkin; vitamin C enriched bitter gourd,
</p>
<p>bathua, mustard, tomato; iron and calcium enriched spinach and bathua;
</p>
<p>and protein enriched beans – broad, lablab, French and garden peas.
</p>
<p>9.3 SINGLE CELL PROTEIN (SCP)
</p>
<p>Conventional agricultural production of cereals, pulses, vegetables, fruits,
</p>
<p>etc., may not be able to meet the demand of food at the rate at which
</p>
<p>human and animal population is increasing. The shift from grain to meat
</p>
<p>diets also creates more demand for cereals as it takes 3-10 Kg of grain to
</p>
<p>produce 1 Kg of meat by animal farming. Can you explain this statement
</p>
<p>in the light of your knowledge of food chains?  More than 25 per cent of
</p>
<p>human population is suffering from hunger and malnutrition. One of the
</p>
<p>alternate sources of proteins for animal and human nutrition is Single
</p>
<p>Cell Protein (SCP).
</p>
<p>Microbes are being grown on an industrial scale as source of good
</p>
<p>protein. Microbes like Spirulina can be grown easily on materials like
</p>
<p>waste water from potato processing plants (containing starch), straw,
</p>
<p>molasses, animal manure and even sewage, to produce large quantities
</p>
<p>and can serve as food rich in protein, minerals, fats, carbohydrate and
</p>
<p>vitamins. Incidentally such utilisation also reduces environmental
</p>
<p>pollution.
</p>
<p>It has been calculated that a 250 Kg cow produces 200 g of protein
</p>
<p>per day.  In the same period, 250g of a micro-organism like Methylophilus
</p>
<p>methylotrophus, because of its high rate of biomass production and
</p>
<p>growth, can be expected to produce 25 tonnes of protein. The fact that
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>STRATEGIES FOR ENHANCEMENT IN FOOD PRODUCTION
</p>
<p>177
</p>
<p>mushrooms are eaten by many people and large scale mushroom culture
</p>
<p>is a growing industry makes it believable that microbes too would
</p>
<p>become acceptable as food.
</p>
<p>9.4 TISSUE CULTURE
</p>
<p>As traditional breeding techniques failed to keep pace with demand and
</p>
<p>to provide sufficiently fast and efficient systems for crop improvement,
</p>
<p>another technology called tissue culture got developed. What does
</p>
<p>tissue culture mean? It was learnt by scientists, during 1950s, that
</p>
<p>whole plants could be regenerated from explants, i.e., any part of a
</p>
<p>plant taken out and grown in a test tube, under sterile conditions in
</p>
<p>special nutrient media. This capacity to generate a whole plant from
</p>
<p>any cell/explant is called totipotency. You will learn how to accomplish
</p>
<p>this in higher classes. It is important to stress here that the nutrient
</p>
<p>medium must provide a carbon source such as sucrose and also
</p>
<p>inorganic salts, vitamins, amino acids and growth regulators like auxins,
</p>
<p>cytokinins etc. By application of these methods it is possible to achieve
</p>
<p>propagation of a large number of plants in very short durations. This
</p>
<p>method of producing thousands of plants through tissue culture is
</p>
<p>called micro-propagation. Each of these plants will be genetically
</p>
<p>identical to the original plant from which they were grown, i.e., they are
</p>
<p>somaclones.  Many important food plants like tomato, banana, apple,
</p>
<p>etc., have been produced on commercial scale using this method. Try
</p>
<p>to visit a tissue culture laboratory with your teacher to better understand
</p>
<p>and appreciate the process.
</p>
<p>Another important application of the method is the recovery of healthy
</p>
<p>plants from diseased plants. Although the plant is infected with a virus,
</p>
<p>the meristem (apical and axillary) is free of virus. Hence, one can remove
</p>
<p>the  meristem and grow it in vitro to obtain virus-free plants. Scientists
</p>
<p>have succeeded in culturing meristems of banana, sugarcane, potato, etc.
</p>
<p>Scientists have even isolated single cells from plants and after
</p>
<p>digesting their cell walls have been able to isolate naked protoplasts
</p>
<p>(surrounded by plasma membranes).  Isolated protoplasts from two
</p>
<p>different varieties of plants – each having a desirable character – can be
</p>
<p>fused to get hybrid protoplasts, which can be further grown to form a
</p>
<p>new plant. These hybrids are called somatic hybrids while the process
</p>
<p>is called somatic hybridisation. Imagine a situation when a protoplast
</p>
<p>of tomato is fused with that of potato, and then they are grown – to form
</p>
<p>new hybrid plants combining tomato and potato characteristics. Well,
</p>
<p>this has been achieved – resulting in formation of pomato; unfortunately
</p>
<p>this plant did not have all the desired combination of characteristics
</p>
<p>for its commercial utilisation.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>178
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>EXERCISES
</p>
<p>1. Explain in brief the role of animal husbandry in human welfare.
</p>
<p>2. If your family owned a dairy farm, what measures would you undertake
to improve the quality and quantity of milk production?
</p>
<p>3. What is meant by the term ‘breed’? What are the objectives of animal
breeding?
</p>
<p>4. Name the methods employed in animal breeding. According to you which
of the methods is best? Why?
</p>
<p>5. What is apiculture? How is it important in our lives?
</p>
<p>6. Discuss the role of fishery in enhancement of food production.
</p>
<p>7. Briefly describe various steps involved in plant breeding.
</p>
<p>8. Explain what is meant by biofortification.
</p>
<p>9. Which part of the plant is best suited for making virus-free plants and
why?
</p>
<p>10. What is the major advantage of producing plants by micropropagation?
</p>
<p>11. Find out what the various components of the medium used for
propagation of an explant in vitro are?
</p>
<p>12. Name any five hybrid varieties of crop plants which have been developed
in India.
</p>
<p>SUMMARY
</p>
<p>Animal husbandry is the practice of taking care and breeding domestic
</p>
<p>animals by applying scientific principles. The ever-increasing demand
</p>
<p>of food from animals and animal products both in terms of quality and
</p>
<p>quantity has been met by good animal husbandry practices. These
</p>
<p>practices include (i) management of farm and farm animals, and (ii)
</p>
<p>animal breeding. In view of the high nutritive value of honey and its
</p>
<p>medicinal importance, there has been a remarkable growth in the practice
</p>
<p>of bee-keeping or apiculture. Fishery is another flourishing industry
</p>
<p>meeting the ever-increasing demand for fish, fish products and other
</p>
<p>aquatic foods.
</p>
<p>Plant breeding may be used to create varieties, which are resistant
</p>
<p>to pathogens and to insect pests. This increases the yield of the food.
</p>
<p>This method has also been used to increase the protein content of the
</p>
<p>plant foods and thereby enhance the quality of food. In India, several
</p>
<p>varieties of different crop plants have been produced. All these measures
</p>
<p>enhance the production of food. Techniques of tissue culture and
</p>
<p>somatic hybridisation offer vast potential for manipulation of plants in
</p>
<p>vitro to produce new varieties.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="acroform"><ol/>
</div>
</body></html>