<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><html xmlns="http://www.w3.org/1999/xhtml">
<head>
<meta name="date" content="2015-04-10T04:08:17Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:PDFVersion" content="1.7"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:title" content="Organisms and Populations.pmd"/>
<meta name="xmp:CreatorTool" content="PageMaker 7.0"/>
<meta name="access_permission:modify_annotations" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_print_degraded" content="true"/>
<meta name="dc:creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="dcterms:created" content="2015-03-12T08:38:10Z"/>
<meta name="Last-Modified" content="2015-04-10T04:08:17Z"/>
<meta name="dcterms:modified" content="2015-04-10T04:08:17Z"/>
<meta name="dc:format" content="application/pdf; version=1.7"/>
<meta name="dc:format" content="application/pdf; version=&quot;1.7 Adobe Extension Level 8&quot;"/>
<meta name="xmpMM:DocumentID" content="9ce2fc76-caee-11e4-0000-768448af145c"/>
<meta name="Last-Save-Date" content="2015-04-10T04:08:17Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:creator_tool" content="PageMaker 7.0"/>
<meta name="access_permission:fill_in_form" content="true"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:modified" content="2015-04-10T04:08:17Z"/>
<meta name="meta:save-date" content="2015-04-10T04:08:17Z"/>
<meta name="pdf:encrypted" content="false"/>
<meta name="dc:title" content="Organisms and Populations.pmd"/>
<meta name="modified" content="2015-04-10T04:08:17Z"/>
<meta name="Content-Length" content="682950"/>
<meta name="Content-Type" content="application/pdf"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="X-Parsed-By" content="org.apache.tika.parser.DefaultParser"/>
<meta name="X-Parsed-By" content="org.apache.tika.parser.pdf.PDFParser"/>
<meta name="creator" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="meta:author" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="meta:creation-date" content="2015-03-12T08:38:10Z"/>
<meta name="created" content="Thu Mar 12 14:08:10 IST 2015"/>
<meta name="pdf:PDFExtensionVersion" content="1.7 Adobe Extension Level 8"/>
<meta name="access_permission:extract_for_accessibility" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:assemble_document" content="true"/>
<meta name="xmpTPg:NPages" content="24"/>
<meta name="Creation-Date" content="2015-03-12T08:38:10Z"/>
<meta name="resourceName" content="lebo113.pdf"/>
<meta name="access_permission:extract_content" content="true"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_print" content="true"/>
<meta name="Author" content="dtpcell9"/>
<meta name="producer" content="GPL Ghostscript 8.61"/>
<meta name="access_permission:can_modify" content="true"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:producer" content="GPL Ghostscript 8.61"/>
<meta name="pdf:docinfo:created" content="2015-03-12T08:38:10Z"/>
<title>Organisms and Populations.pmd</title>
</head>
<body><div class="page"><p/>
<p>Diversity is not only a characteristic of living organisms but
</p>
<p>also of content in biology textbooks. Biology is presented either
</p>
<p>as botany, zoology and microbiology or as classical and
</p>
<p>modern. The latter is a euphemism for molecular aspects of
</p>
<p>biology. Luckily we have many threads which weave the
</p>
<p>different areas of biological information into a unifying
</p>
<p>principle. Ecology is one such thread which gives us a holistic
</p>
<p>perspective to biology. The essence of biological understanding
</p>
<p>is to know how organisms, while remaining an individual,
</p>
<p>interact with other organisms and physical habitats as a group
</p>
<p>and hence behave like organised wholes, i.e., population,
</p>
<p>community, ecosystem or even as the whole biosphere.
</p>
<p>Ecology explains to us all this. A particular aspect of this is the
</p>
<p>study of anthropogenic environmental degradation and the
</p>
<p>socio-political issues it has raised. This unit describes as well as
</p>
<p>takes a critical view of the above aspects.
</p>
<p>Chapter 13
</p>
<p>Organisms and Populations
</p>
<p>Chapter 14
</p>
<p>Ecosystem
</p>
<p>Chapter 15
</p>
<p>Biodiversity and Conservation
</p>
<p>Chapter 16
</p>
<p>Environmental  Issues
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>Ramdeo Misra is revered as the Father of Ecology in India. Born on 26 August
</p>
<p>1908,  Ramdeo Misra obtained Ph.D in Ecology (1937) under Prof. W. H. Pearsall,
</p>
<p>FRS, from Leeds University in UK. He established  teaching and research  in
</p>
<p>ecology at the Department of Botany of the Banaras Hindu University,
</p>
<p>Varanasi. His research laid the foundations for understanding of tropical
</p>
<p>communities and their succession, environmental responses of plant
</p>
<p>populations and productivity and nutrient cycling in tropical forest and
</p>
<p>grassland ecosystems. Misra formulated the first postgraduate course in
</p>
<p>ecology in India. Over 50 scholars obtained Ph. D degree under his supervision
</p>
<p>and moved on to other universities and research institutes to initiate ecology
</p>
<p>teaching and research across the country.
</p>
<p>He was honoured with the Fellowships of the Indian National Science
</p>
<p>Academy and World Academy of Arts and Science, and the prestigious Sanjay
</p>
<p>Gandhi Award in Environment and Ecology. Due to his efforts, the
</p>
<p>Government of India established the National Committee for Environmental
</p>
<p>Planning and Coordination (1972) which, in later years, paved the way
</p>
<p>for the establishment of the Ministry of Environment and Forests (1984).
</p>
<p>RAMDEO MISRA
(1908-1998)
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>Our living world is fascinatingly diverse and amazingly
</p>
<p>complex.  We can try to understand its complexity by
</p>
<p>investigating processes at various levels of biological
</p>
<p>organisation–macromolecules, cells, tissues, organs,
</p>
<p>individual organisms, population, communities and
</p>
<p>ecosystems and biomes. At any level of biological
</p>
<p>organisation we can ask two types of questions – for
</p>
<p>example, when we hear the bulbul singing early morning
</p>
<p>in the garden, we may ask – ‘How does the bird sing?’
</p>
<p>Or, ‘Why does the bird sing ?’  The ‘how-type’ questions
</p>
<p>seek the mechanism behind the process while the ‘why-
</p>
<p>type’ questions seek the significance of the process. For
</p>
<p>the first question in our example, the answer might be in
</p>
<p>terms of the operation of the voice box and the vibrating
</p>
<p>bone in the bird, whereas for the second question the
</p>
<p>answer may lie in the bird’s need to communicate with its
</p>
<p>mate during breeding season. When you observe nature
</p>
<p>around you with a scientific frame of mind you will
</p>
<p>certainly come up with many interesting questions of both
</p>
<p>types - Why are night-blooming flowers generally white?
</p>
<p>How does the bee know which flower has nectar? Why
</p>
<p>does cactus have so many thorns? How does the chick
</p>
<p>recognise her own mother?, and so on.
</p>
<p>CHAPTER 13
</p>
<p>ORGANISMS AND POPULATIONS
</p>
<p>13.1 Organism and Its
</p>
<p>Environment
</p>
<p>13.2 Populations
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>220
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>You have already learnt in previous classes that Ecology is a subject
</p>
<p>which studies the interactions among organisms and between the
</p>
<p>organism and its physical (abiotic) environment.
</p>
<p>Ecology is basically concerned with four levels of biological
</p>
<p>organisation – organisms, populations, communities and biomes.  In this
</p>
<p>chapter we explore ecology at organismic and population levels.
</p>
<p>13.1 ORGANISM AND ITS ENVIRONMENT
</p>
<p>Ecology at the organismic level is essentially physiological ecology which
</p>
<p>tries to understand how different organisms are adapted to their
</p>
<p>environments in terms of not only survival but also reproduction.  You
</p>
<p>may have learnt in earlier classes how the rotation of  our planet around
</p>
<p>the Sun and the tilt of its axis cause annual variations in the intensity
</p>
<p>and duration of temperature, resulting in distinct seasons.  These
</p>
<p>variations together with annual variation in precipitation (remember
</p>
<p>precipitation includes both rain and snow) account for the formation of
</p>
<p>major biomes such as desert, rain forest and tundra (Figure 13.1).
</p>
<p>Figure 13.1 Biome distribution with respect to annual temperature and precipitation
</p>
<p>Regional and local variations within each biome lead to the formation of a
</p>
<p>wide variety of habitats. Major biomes of India are shown in Figure 13.2.
</p>
<p>On planet Earth, life exists not just in a few favourable habitats but even
</p>
<p>in extreme and harsh habitats – scorching Rajasthan desert, perpetually
</p>
<p>rain-soaked Meghalaya forests, deep ocean trenches, torrential streams,
</p>
<p>permafrost polar regions, high mountain tops, boiling thermal springs,
</p>
<p>and stinking compost pits, to name a few.  Even our intestine is a unique
</p>
<p>habitat for hundreds of species of microbes.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>221
</p>
<p>ORGANISMS AND POPULATIONS
</p>
<p>What are the key elements that lead to so much variation in the
</p>
<p>physical and chemical conditions of different habitats? The most
</p>
<p>important ones are temperature, water, light and soil.  We must remember
</p>
<p>that the physico-chemical (abiotic) components alone do not characterise
</p>
<p>the habitat of an organism completely; the habitat includes biotic
</p>
<p>components also – pathogens, parasites, predators and competitors – of
</p>
<p>the organism with which they interact constantly.  We assume that over a
</p>
<p>period of time, the organism had through natural selection, evolved
</p>
<p>adaptations to optimise its survival and reproduction in its habitat.
</p>
<p>13.1.1 Major Abiotic Factors
</p>
<p>Temperature: Temperature is the most ecologically relevant
</p>
<p>environmental factor.  You are aware that the average temperature on
</p>
<p>land varies seasonally, decreases progressively from the equator towards
</p>
<p>the poles and from plains to the mountain tops. It ranges from subzero
</p>
<p>levels in polar areas and high altitudes to &gt;500C in tropical deserts in
</p>
<p>summer. There are, however, unique habitats such as thermal springs
</p>
<p>and deep-sea hydrothermal vents where average temperatures exceed
</p>
<p>1000 C.  It is general knowledge that mango trees do not and cannot grow
</p>
<p>in temperate countries like Canada and Germany, snow leopards are not
</p>
<p>found in Kerala forests and tuna fish are rarely caught beyond tropical
</p>
<p>Figure 13.2 Major biomes of India : (a) Tropical rain forest; (b) Deciduous forest;
(c) Desert; (d) Sea coast
</p>
<p> (a)  (b)
</p>
<p> (c)  (d)
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>222
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>latitudes in the ocean. You can readily appreciate the significance of
</p>
<p>temperature to living organisms when you realise that it affects the kinetics
</p>
<p>of enzymes and through it the basal metabolism, activity and other
</p>
<p>physiological functions of the organism. A few organisms can tolerate and
</p>
<p>thrive in a wide range of temperatures (they are called eurythermal), but, a
</p>
<p>vast majority of them are restricted to a narrow range of temperatures (such
</p>
<p>organisms are called stenothermal ). The levels of thermal tolerance of
</p>
<p>different species determine to a large extent their geographical distribution.
</p>
<p>Can you think of a few eurythermal and stenothermal animals and
</p>
<p>plants?
</p>
<p>In recent years, there has been a growing concern about the gradually
</p>
<p>increasing average global temperatures (Chapter 16). If this trend
</p>
<p>continues, would you expect the distributional range of some species to
</p>
<p>be affected?
</p>
<p>Water: Next to temperature, water is the most important factor influencing
</p>
<p>the life of organisms. In fact, life on earth originated in water and is
</p>
<p>unsustainable without water. Its availability is so limited in deserts that
</p>
<p>only special adaptations make it possible to live there. The productivity
</p>
<p>and distribution of plants is also heavily dependent on water.  You might
</p>
<p>think that organisms living in oceans, lakes and rivers should not face
</p>
<p>any water-related problems, but it is not true.  For aquatic organisms the
</p>
<p>quality (chemical composition, pH) of water becomes important. The salt
</p>
<p>concentration (measured as salinity in parts per thousand), is less than
</p>
<p>5 in inland waters, 30-35 in the sea and &gt; 100 in some hypersaline
</p>
<p>lagoons. Some organisms are tolerant of a wide range of salinities
</p>
<p>(euryhaline) but others are restricted to a narrow range (stenohaline).
</p>
<p>Many freshwater animals cannot live for long in sea water and vice versa
</p>
<p>because of the osmotic problems, they would face.
</p>
<p>Light: Since plants produce food through photosynthesis, a process which
</p>
<p>is only possible when sunlight is available as a source of energy, we can
</p>
<p>quickly understand the importance of light for living organisms,
</p>
<p>particularly autotrophs.  Many species of small plants (herbs and shrubs)
</p>
<p>growing in forests are adapted to photosynthesise optimally under very
</p>
<p>low light conditions because they are constantly overshadowed by tall,
</p>
<p>canopied trees. Many plants are also dependent on sunlight to meet their
</p>
<p>photoperiodic requirement for flowering. For many animals too, light is
</p>
<p>important in that they use the diurnal and seasonal variations in light
</p>
<p>intensity and duration (photoperiod) as cues for timing their foraging,
</p>
<p>reproductive and migratory activities. The availability of light on land is
</p>
<p>closely linked with that of temperature since the sun is the source for
</p>
<p>both. But, deep (&gt;500m) in the oceans, the environment is perpetually
</p>
<p>dark and its inhabitants are not aware of the existence of a celestial source
</p>
<p>of energy called Sun. What, then is their source of energy?.  The spectral
</p>
<p>quality of solar radiation is also important for life.  The UV component of
</p>
<p>the spectrum is harmful to many organisms while not all the colour
</p>
<p>components of the visible spectrum are available for marine plants living
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>223
</p>
<p>ORGANISMS AND POPULATIONS
</p>
<p>at different depths of the ocean. Among the red, green and brown algae
</p>
<p>that inhabit the sea, which is likely to be found in the deepest waters?
</p>
<p>Why?
</p>
<p>Soil: The nature and properties of soil in different places vary; it is
</p>
<p>dependent on the climate, the weathering process, whether soil is
</p>
<p>transported or sedimentary and how soil development occurred. Various
</p>
<p>characteristics of the soil such as soil composition, grain size and
</p>
<p>aggregation determine the percolation and water holding capacity of the
</p>
<p>soils. These characteristics along with parameters such as pH, mineral
</p>
<p>composition and topography determine to a large extent the vegetation in
</p>
<p>any area. This in turn dictates the type of animals that can be supported.
</p>
<p>Similarly, in the aquatic environment, the sediment-characteristics often
</p>
<p>determine the type of benthic animals that can thrive there.
</p>
<p>13.1.2 Responses to Abiotic Factors
</p>
<p>Having realised that the abiotic conditions of many habitats may vary
</p>
<p>drastically in time, we now ask–how do the organisms living in such
</p>
<p>habitats cope or manage with stressful conditions? But before attempting
</p>
<p>to answer this question, we should perhaps ask first why a highly variable
</p>
<p>external environment should bother organisms after all.  One would expect
</p>
<p>that during the course of millions of years of their existence, many species
</p>
<p>would have evolved a relatively constant internal (within the body)
</p>
<p>environment that permits all biochemical reactions and physiological
</p>
<p>functions to proceed with maximal
</p>
<p>efficiency and thus, enhance the overall
</p>
<p>‘fitness’ of the species.  This constancy, for
</p>
<p>example, could be in terms of optimal
</p>
<p>temperature and osmotic concentration of
</p>
<p>body fluids. Ideally then, the organism
</p>
<p>should try to maintain the constancy of its
</p>
<p>internal environment (a process called
</p>
<p>homeostasis) despite varying external
</p>
<p>environmental conditions that tend to
</p>
<p>upset its homeostasis.  Let us take an
</p>
<p>analogy to clarify this important concept.
</p>
<p>Suppose a person is able to perform his/
</p>
<p>her best when the temperature is 250C and
</p>
<p>wishes to maintain it so, even when it is
</p>
<p>scorchingly hot or freezingly cold outside.
</p>
<p>It could be achieved at home, in the car while travelling, and at workplace
</p>
<p>by using an air conditioner in summer and heater in winter. Then his/
</p>
<p>her performance would be always maximal regardless of the weather
</p>
<p>around him/her. Here the person’s homeostasis is accomplished, not
</p>
<p>through physiological, but artificial means. How do other living
</p>
<p>organisms cope with the situation? Let us look at various possibilities
</p>
<p>(Figure 13.3).
</p>
<p>Figure 13.3 Diagrammatic representation of
organismic response
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>224
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>(i) Regulate: Some organisms are able to maintain homeostasis by
</p>
<p>physiological (sometimes behavioural also) means which ensures
</p>
<p>constant body temperature, constant osmotic concentration, etc.
</p>
<p>All birds and mammals, and a very few lower vertebrate and
</p>
<p>invertebrate species are indeed capable of such regulation
</p>
<p>(thermoregulation and osmoregulation).  Evolutionary biologists
</p>
<p>believe that the ‘success’ of mammals is largely due to their ability
</p>
<p>to maintain a constant body temperature and thrive whether they
</p>
<p>live in Antarctica or in the Sahara desert.
</p>
<p>The mechanisms used by most mammals to regulate their body
</p>
<p>temperature are similar to the ones that we humans use. We maintain
</p>
<p>a constant body temperature of 370C. In summer, when outside
</p>
<p>temperature is more than our body temperature, we sweat profusely.
</p>
<p>The resulting evaporative cooling, similar to what happens with a
</p>
<p>desert cooler in operation, brings down the body temperature. In
</p>
<p>winter when the temperature is much lower than 370C, we start to
</p>
<p>shiver, a kind of exercise which produces heat and raises the body
</p>
<p>temperature.  Plants, on the other hand, do not have such
</p>
<p>mechanisms to maintain internal temperatures.
</p>
<p>(ii) Conform: An overwhelming majority (99 per cent) of animals and
</p>
<p>nearly all plants cannot maintain a constant internal environment.
</p>
<p>Their body temperature changes with the ambient temperature. In
</p>
<p>aquatic animals, the osmotic concentration of the body fluids
</p>
<p>change with that of the ambient water osmotic concentration. These
</p>
<p>animals and plants are simply conformers. Considering the benefits
</p>
<p>of a constant internal environment to the organism, we must ask
</p>
<p>why these conformers had not evolved to become regulators. Recall
</p>
<p>the human analogy we used above; much as they like, how many
</p>
<p>people can really afford an air conditioner? Many simply ‘sweat it
</p>
<p>out’ and resign themselves to suboptimal performance in hot
</p>
<p>summer months. Thermoregulation is energetically expensive for
</p>
<p>many organisms. This is particularly true for small animals like
</p>
<p>shrews and humming birds.  Heat loss or heat gain is a function of
</p>
<p>surface area. Since small animals have a larger surface area relative
</p>
<p>to their volume, they tend to lose body heat very fast when it is cold
</p>
<p>outside; then they have to expend much energy to generate body
</p>
<p>heat through metabolism. This is the main reason why very small
</p>
<p>animals are rarely found in polar regions. During the course of
</p>
<p>evolution, the costs and benefits of maintaining a constant internal
</p>
<p>environment are taken into consideration. Some species have evolved
</p>
<p>the ability to regulate, but only over a limited range of environmental
</p>
<p>conditions, beyond which they simply conform.
</p>
<p>If the stressful external conditions are localised or remain only
</p>
<p>for a short duration, the organism has two other alternatives.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>225
</p>
<p>ORGANISMS AND POPULATIONS
</p>
<p>(iii) Migrate : The organism can move away temporarily from the
</p>
<p>stressful habitat to a more hospitable area and return when stressful
</p>
<p>period is over. In human analogy, this strategy is like a person
</p>
<p>moving from Delhi to Shimla for the duration of summer. Many
</p>
<p>animals, particularly birds, during winter undertake long-distance
</p>
<p>migrations to more hospitable areas. Every winter the famous
</p>
<p>Keolado National Park (Bharatpur) in Rajasthan host thousands of
</p>
<p>migratory birds coming from Siberia and other extremely cold
</p>
<p>northern regions.
</p>
<p>(iv) Suspend: In bacteria, fungi and lower plants, various kinds of thick-
</p>
<p>walled spores are formed which help them to survive unfavourable
</p>
<p>conditions – these germinate on availability of suitable environment.
</p>
<p>In higher plants, seeds and some other vegetative reproductive
</p>
<p>structures serve as means to tide over periods of stress besides helping
</p>
<p>in dispersal – they germinate to form new plants under favourable
</p>
<p>moisture and temperature conditions. They do so by reducing their
</p>
<p>metabolic activity and going into a state of ‘dormancy’.
</p>
<p>In animals, the organism, if unable to migrate, might avoid the
</p>
<p>stress by escaping in time. The familiar case of bears going into
</p>
<p>hibernation during winter is an example of escape in time. Some
</p>
<p>snails and fish go into aestivation to avoid summer–related
</p>
<p>problems-heat and dessication. Under unfavourable conditions
</p>
<p>many zooplankton species in lakes and ponds are known to enter
</p>
<p>diapause, a stage of suspended development.
</p>
<p>13.1.3 Adaptations
</p>
<p>While considering the various alternatives available to organisms for
</p>
<p>coping with extremes in their environment, we have seen that some are
</p>
<p>able to respond through certain physiological adjustments while others
</p>
<p>do so behaviourally (migrating temporarily to a less stressful habitat).
</p>
<p>These responses are also actually, their adaptations. So, we can say that
</p>
<p>adaptation is any attribute of the organism (morphological, physiological,
</p>
<p>behavioural) that enables the organism to survive and reproduce in its
</p>
<p>habitat. Many adaptations have evolved over a long evolutionary time
</p>
<p>and are genetically fixed. In the absence of an external source of water,
</p>
<p>the kangaroo rat in North American deserts is capable of meeting all its
</p>
<p>water requirements through its internal fat oxidation (in which water is
</p>
<p>a by product).  It also has the ability to concentrate its urine so that
</p>
<p>minimal volume of water is used to remove excretory products.
</p>
<p>Many desert plants have a thick cuticle on their leaf surfaces and
</p>
<p>have their stomata arranged in deep pits to minimise water loss through
</p>
<p>transpiration.  They also have a special photosynthetic pathway (CAM)
</p>
<p>that enables their stomata to remain closed during day time.  Some desert
</p>
<p>plants like Opuntia, have no leaves – they are reduced to spines–and the
</p>
<p>photosynthetic function is taken over by the flattened stems.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>226
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>Mammals from colder climates generally have shorter ears and limbs
</p>
<p>to minimise heat loss. (This is called the Allen’s Rule.)  In the polar seas
</p>
<p>aquatic mammals like seals have a thick layer of fat (blubber) below their
</p>
<p>skin that acts as an insulator and reduces loss of body heat.
</p>
<p>Some organisms possess adaptations that are physiological which
</p>
<p>allow them to respond quickly to a stressful situation.  If you had ever
</p>
<p>been to any high altitude place (&gt;3,500m Rohtang Pass near Manali and
</p>
<p>Mansarovar, in China occupied Tibet) you must have experienced what
</p>
<p>is called altitude sickness.  Its symptoms include nausea, fatigue and
</p>
<p>heart palpitations. This is because in the low atmospheric pressure of
</p>
<p>high altitudes, the body does not get enough oxygen. But, gradually you
</p>
<p>get acclimatised and stop experiencing altitude sickness. How did your
</p>
<p>body solve this problem? The body compensates low oxygen availability
</p>
<p>by increasing red blood cell production, decreasing the binding affinity
</p>
<p>of hemoglobin and by increasing breathing rate. Many tribes live in the
</p>
<p>high altitude of Himalayas. Find out if they normally have a higher red
</p>
<p>blood cell count (or total hemoglobin) than people living in the plains.
</p>
<p>In most animals, the metabolic reactions and hence all the
</p>
<p>physiological functions proceed optimally in a narrow temperature range
</p>
<p>(in humans, it is 370C). But there are microbes (archaebacteria) that
</p>
<p>flourish in hot springs and deep sea hydrothermal vents where
</p>
<p>temperatures far exceed 1000C. How is this possible?
</p>
<p>Many fish thrive in Antarctic waters where the temperature is always
</p>
<p>below zero. How do they manage to keep their body fluids from freezing?
</p>
<p>A large variety of marine invertebrates and fish live at great depths in
</p>
<p>the ocean where the pressure could be &gt;100 times the normal atmospheric
</p>
<p>pressure that we experience. How do they live under such crushing
</p>
<p>pressures and do they have any special enzymes? Organisms living in
</p>
<p>such extreme environments show a fascinating array of biochemical
</p>
<p>adaptations.
</p>
<p>Some organisms show behavioural responses to cope with variations
</p>
<p>in their environment. Desert lizards lack the physiological ability that
</p>
<p>mammals have to deal with the high temperatures of their habitat, but
</p>
<p>manage to keep their body temperature fairly constant by behavioural
</p>
<p>means.  They bask in the sun and absorb heat when their body
</p>
<p>temperature drops below the comfort zone, but move into shade when
</p>
<p>the ambient temperature starts increasing. Some species are capable of
</p>
<p>burrowing into the soil to hide and escape from the above-ground heat.
</p>
<p>13.2 POPULATIONS
</p>
<p>13.2.1 Population Attributes
</p>
<p>In nature, we rarely find isolated, single individuals of any species; majority
</p>
<p>of them live in groups in a well defined geographical area, share or compete
</p>
<p>for similar resources, potentially interbreed and thus constitute a
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>227
</p>
<p>ORGANISMS AND POPULATIONS
</p>
<p>population. Although the term interbreeding implies sexual reproduction,
</p>
<p>a group of individuals resulting from even asexual reproduction is also
</p>
<p>generally considered a population for the purpose of ecological studies.
</p>
<p>All the cormorants in a wetland, rats in an abandoned dwelling, teakwood
</p>
<p>trees in a forest tract, bacteria in a culture plate and lotus plants in a
</p>
<p>pond, are some examples of a population.  In earlier chapters you have
</p>
<p>learnt that although an individual organism is the one that has to cope
</p>
<p>with a changed environment, it is at the population level that natural
</p>
<p>selection operates to evolve the desired traits. Population ecology is,
</p>
<p>therefore, an important area of ecology because it links ecology to
</p>
<p>population genetics and evolution.
</p>
<p>A population has certain attributes that an individual organism does
</p>
<p>not. An individual may have births and deaths, but a population has birth
</p>
<p>rates and death rates. In a population these rates refer to per capita births
</p>
<p>and deaths, respectively. The rates, hence, expressed is change in numbers
</p>
<p>(increase or decrease) with respect to members of the population. Here is an
</p>
<p>example. If in a pond there are 20 lotus plants last year and through
</p>
<p>reproduction 8 new plants are added, taking the current population to 28,
</p>
<p>we calculate the birth rate as 8/20 = 0.4 offspring per lotus per year. If 4
</p>
<p>individuals in a laboratory population of 40 fruitflies died during a specified
</p>
<p>time interval, say a week, the death rate in the population during that period
</p>
<p>is 4/40 = 0.1 individuals per fruitfly per week.
</p>
<p>Another attribute characteristic of a population is sex ratio. An
</p>
<p>individual is either a male or a female but a population has a sex ratio
</p>
<p>(e.g., 60 per cent of the population are females and 40 per cent males).
</p>
<p>A population at any given time is composed of individuals of different
</p>
<p>ages. If the age distribution (per cent individuals of a given age or age
</p>
<p>group) is plotted for the population, the resulting structure is called an
</p>
<p>age pyramid (Figure 13.4). For human population, the age pyramids
</p>
<p>generally show age distribution of males and females in a combined
</p>
<p>diagram. The shape of the pyramids reflects the growth status of the
</p>
<p>population - (a) whether it is growing, (b) stable or (c) declining.
</p>
<p>Figure 13.4 Representation of age pyramids for human population
</p>
<p>The size of the population tells us a lot about its status in the habitat.
</p>
<p>Whatever ecological processes we wish to investigate in a population, be
</p>
<p>it the outcome of competition with another species, the impact of a
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>228
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>predator or the effect of a pesticide application, we always evaluate them
</p>
<p>in terms of any change in the population size. The size, in nature, could
</p>
<p>be as low as &lt;10 (Siberian cranes at Bharatpur wetlands in any year) or
</p>
<p>go into millions (Chlamydomonas in a pond). Population size, more
</p>
<p>technically called population density (designated as N), need not
</p>
<p>necessarily be measured in numbers only. Although total number is
</p>
<p>generally the most appropriate measure of population density, it is in
</p>
<p>some cases either meaningless or difficult to determine.  In an area,  if
</p>
<p>there are 200 Parthenium plants but only a single huge banyan tree with
</p>
<p>a large canopy, stating that the population density of banyan is low relative
</p>
<p>to that of Parthenium amounts to underestimating the enormous role of
</p>
<p>the Banyan in that community. In such cases, the per cent cover or biomass
</p>
<p>is a more meaningful measure of the population size. Total number is
</p>
<p>again not an easily adoptable measure if the population is huge and
</p>
<p>counting is impossible or very time-consuming. If you have a dense
</p>
<p>laboratory culture of bacteria  in a petri dish what is the best measure to
</p>
<p>report its density?  Sometimes, for certain ecological investigations, there
</p>
<p>is no need to know the absolute population densities; relative densities
</p>
<p>serve the purpose equally well.  For instance, the number of fish caught
</p>
<p>per trap is good enough measure of its total population density in the lake.
</p>
<p>We are mostly obliged to estimate population sizes indirectly, without
</p>
<p>actually counting them or seeing them. The tiger census in our national
</p>
<p>parks and tiger reserves is often based on pug marks and fecal pellets.
</p>
<p>13.2.2 Population Growth
</p>
<p>The size of a population for any species is not a static parameter.  It keeps
</p>
<p>changing in time, depending on various factors including food availability,
</p>
<p>predation pressure and adverse weather.  In fact, it is these changes in
</p>
<p>population density that give us some idea of what is happening to the
</p>
<p>population – whether it is flourishing or declining.  Whatever might be
</p>
<p>the ultimate reasons, the density of a population in a given habitat during
</p>
<p>a given period, fluctuates due to changes in four basic processes, two of
</p>
<p>which (natality and immigration) contribute to an increase in population
</p>
<p>density and two (mortality and emigration) to a decrease.
</p>
<p>(i) Natality refers to the number of births during a given period in the
</p>
<p>population that are added to the initial density.
</p>
<p>(ii) Mortality is the number of deaths in the population during a given
</p>
<p>period.
</p>
<p>(iii) Immigration is the number of individuals of the same species that
</p>
<p>have come into the habitat from elsewhere during the time period
</p>
<p>under consideration.
</p>
<p>(iv) Emigration is the number of individuals of the population who
</p>
<p>left the habitat and gone elsewhere during the time period under
</p>
<p>consideration.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>229
</p>
<p>ORGANISMS AND POPULATIONS
</p>
<p>So, if N is the population density at time t, then its density at time t +1 is
</p>
<p>N
t+1
</p>
<p> = N
t
 + [(B + I) – (D + E)]
</p>
<p>You can see from the above equation that population density will
</p>
<p>increase if the number of births plus the number of immigrants (B + I) is
</p>
<p>more than the number of deaths plus the number of emigrants (D + E),
</p>
<p>otherwise it will decrease.  Under normal conditions, births and deaths
</p>
<p>are the most important factors influencing population density, the other
</p>
<p>two factors assuming importance only under special conditions.  For
</p>
<p>instance, if a new habitat is just being colonised, immigration may
</p>
<p>contribute more significantly to population growth than birth rates.
</p>
<p>Growth Models : Does the growth of a population with time show any
</p>
<p>specific and predictable pattern? We have been concerned about unbridled
</p>
<p>human population growth and problems created by it in our country
</p>
<p>and it is therefore natural for us to be curious if different animal
</p>
<p>populations in nature behave the same way or show some restraints on
</p>
<p>growth. Perhaps we can learn a lesson or two from nature on how to
</p>
<p>control population growth.
</p>
<p>(i) Exponential growth: Resource (food and space) availability is
</p>
<p>obviously essential for the unimpeded growth of a population.
</p>
<p>Ideally, when resources in the habitat are unlimited, each species
</p>
<p>has the ability to realise fully its innate potential to grow in number,
</p>
<p>as Darwin observed while developing his theory of natural selection.
</p>
<p>Then the population grows in an exponential or geometric fashion.
</p>
<p>If in a population of size N, the birth rates (not total number but
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>230
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>per capita births) are represented as b and death rates (again, per
</p>
<p>capita death rates) as d, then the increase or decrease in N during a
</p>
<p>unit time period  t  (dN/dt) will be
</p>
<p>dN/dt = (b – d) × N
</p>
<p>Let (b–d) = r, then
</p>
<p>dN/dt = rN
</p>
<p>The r in this equation is called the ‘intrinsic rate of natural increase’
</p>
<p>and is a very important parameter chosen for assessing impacts of
</p>
<p>any biotic or abiotic factor on population growth.
</p>
<p>To give you some idea about the magnitude of r values, for the
</p>
<p>Norway rat the r is 0.015, and for the flour beetle it is 0.12.  In
</p>
<p>1981, the r value for human population in India was 0.0205.  Find
</p>
<p>out what the current r value is.  For calculating it, you need to
</p>
<p>know the birth rates and death rates.
</p>
<p>The above equation describes the exponential or geometric growth
</p>
<p>pattern of a population (Figure 13.5) and results in a J-shaped curve
</p>
<p>when we plot N in relation to time. If you are familiar with basic
</p>
<p>calculus, you can derive the integral form of the
</p>
<p>exponential growth equation as
</p>
<p>N
t
 = N
</p>
<p>0
 ert
</p>
<p>  where
</p>
<p>N
t
 = Population density after time t
</p>
<p>N
0
 = Population density at time zero
</p>
<p>r = intrinsic rate of natural increase
</p>
<p>e = the base of natural logarithms (2.71828)
</p>
<p>Any species growing exponentially under unlimited
</p>
<p>resource conditions can reach enormous population
</p>
<p>densities in a short time. Darwin showed how even
</p>
<p>a slow growing animal like elephant could reach
</p>
<p>enormous numbers in the absence of checks. The
</p>
<p>following is an anecdote popularly narrated to
</p>
<p>demonstrate dramatically how fast a huge
</p>
<p>population could build up when growing
</p>
<p>exponentially.
</p>
<p>The king and the minister sat for a chess game. The king, confident
</p>
<p>of winning the game, was ready to accept any bet proposed by the
</p>
<p>minister. The minister humbly said that if he won, he wanted only
</p>
<p>some wheat grains, the quantity of which is to be calculated by placing
</p>
<p>on the chess board one grain in Square 1, then two in Square 2,
</p>
<p>then four in Square 3, and eight in Square 4, and so on, doubling each
</p>
<p>time the previous quantity of wheat on the next square until all the 64
</p>
<p>squares were filled.  The king accepted the seemingly silly bet and started
</p>
<p>the game, but unluckily for him, the minister won. The king felt that fulfilling
</p>
<p>Figure 13.5 Population growth curve
a when responses are not
limiting the growth, plot is
exponential,
b when responses are limiting
the growth, plot is logistic,
K is carrying capacity
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>231
</p>
<p>ORGANISMS AND POPULATIONS
</p>
<p>the minister’s bet was so easy.  He started with a single grain on
</p>
<p>the first square and proceeded to fill the other squares following
</p>
<p>minister’s suggested procedure, but by the time he covered half the
</p>
<p>chess board, the king realised to his dismay that all the wheat
</p>
<p>produced in his entire kingdom pooled together would still be
</p>
<p>inadequate to cover all the 64 squares. Now think of a tiny
</p>
<p>Paramecium starting with just one individual and through binary
</p>
<p>fission, doubling in numbers every day, and imagine what a mind-
</p>
<p>boggling population size it would reach in 64 days. (provided food
</p>
<p>and space remain unlimited)
</p>
<p>(ii) Logistic growth: No population of any species in nature has at its
</p>
<p>disposal unlimited resources to permit exponential growth. This
</p>
<p>leads to competition between individuals for limited resources.
</p>
<p>Eventually, the ‘fittest’ individual will survive and reproduce.  The
</p>
<p>governments of many countries have also realised this fact and
</p>
<p>introduced various restraints with a view to limit human population
</p>
<p>growth. In nature, a given habitat has enough resources to support
</p>
<p>a maximum possible number, beyond which no further growth is
</p>
<p>possible. Let us call this limit as nature’s carrying capacity (K) for
</p>
<p>that species in that habitat.
</p>
<p>A population growing in a habitat with limited resources show
</p>
<p>initially a lag phase, followed by phases of acceleration and
</p>
<p>deceleration and finally an asymptote, when the population density
</p>
<p>reaches the carrying capacity. A plot of N in relation to time (t)
</p>
<p>results in a sigmoid curve. This type of population growth is called
</p>
<p>Verhulst-Pearl Logistic Growth (Figure 13.5) and is described by
</p>
<p>the following equation:
</p>
<p>dN/dt = 
K N
</p>
<p>rN
K
</p>
<p>− 
 
 
</p>
<p>Where N = Population density at time t
</p>
<p>r = Intrinsic rate of natural increase
</p>
<p>K = Carrying capacity
</p>
<p>Since resources for growth for most animal populations are finite
</p>
<p>and become limiting sooner or later, the logistic growth model is
</p>
<p>considered a more realistic one.
</p>
<p>Gather from Government Census data the population figures
</p>
<p>for India for the last 100 years, plot them and check which growth
</p>
<p>pattern is evident.
</p>
<p>13.2.3 Life History Variation
</p>
<p>Populations evolve to maximise their reproductive  fitness, also called
</p>
<p>Darwinian fitness (high r value), in the habitat in which they live.  Under
</p>
<p>a particular set of selection pressures, organisms evolve towards the most
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>232
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>efficient reproductive strategy. Some organisms breed only once in their
</p>
<p>lifetime (Pacific salmon fish, bamboo) while others breed many times
</p>
<p>during their lifetime (most birds and mammals). Some produce a large
</p>
<p>number of small-sized offspring (Oysters, pelagic fishes) while others
</p>
<p>produce a small number of large-sized offspring (birds, mammals).  So,
</p>
<p>which is desirable for maximising fitness?  Ecologists suggest that life
</p>
<p>history traits of organisms have evolved in relation to the constraints
</p>
<p>imposed by the abiotic and biotic components of the habitat in which
</p>
<p>they live. Evolution of life history traits in different species is currently an
</p>
<p>important area of research being conducted by ecologists.
</p>
<p>13.2.4 Population Interactions
</p>
<p>Can you think of any natural habitat on earth that is inhabited just by a
</p>
<p>single species?  There is no such habitat and such a situation is even
</p>
<p>inconceivable.  For any species, the minimal requirement is one more
</p>
<p>species on which it can feed.  Even a plant species, which makes its own
</p>
<p>food, cannot survive alone; it needs soil microbes to break down the organic
</p>
<p>matter in soil and return the inorganic nutrients for absorption. And then,
</p>
<p>how will the plant manage pollination without an animal agent?  It is
</p>
<p>obvious that in nature, animals, plants and microbes do not and cannot
</p>
<p>live in isolation but interact in various ways to form a biological
</p>
<p>community.  Even in minimal communities, many interactive linkages
</p>
<p>exist, although all may not be readily apparent.
</p>
<p>Interspecific interactions arise from the interaction of populations of
</p>
<p>two different species. They could be beneficial, detrimental or neutral
</p>
<p>(neither harm nor benefit) to one of the species or both. Assigning a ‘+’
</p>
<p>sign for beneficial interaction, ‘-’ sign for detrimental and 0 for neutral
</p>
<p>interaction, let us look at all the possible outcomes of interspecific
</p>
<p>interactions (Table13.1).
</p>
<p>Both the species benefit in mutualism and both lose in competition in
</p>
<p>their interactions with each other. In both parasitism and predation only
</p>
<p>one species benefits (parasite and predator, respectively) and the interaction
</p>
<p>Species A Species B Name of  Interaction
</p>
<p>+ + Mutualism
</p>
<p>– – Competition
</p>
<p>+ – Predation
</p>
<p>+ – Parasitism
</p>
<p>+ 0 Commensalism
</p>
<p>– 0 Amensalism
</p>
<p>Table 13.1 : Population Interactions
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>233
</p>
<p>ORGANISMS AND POPULATIONS
</p>
<p>is detrimental to the other species (host and prey, respectively).
</p>
<p>The interaction where one species is benefitted and the other is neither
</p>
<p>benefitted nor harmed is called commensalism. In amensalism on
</p>
<p>the other hand one species is harmed whereas the other is
</p>
<p>unaffected. Predation, parasitism and commensalism share a common
</p>
<p>characteristic– the interacting species live closely together.
</p>
<p>(i) Predation: What would happen to all the energy fixed by
</p>
<p>autotrophic organisms if the community has no animals to eat the
</p>
<p>plants?  You can think of predation as nature’s way of transferring
</p>
<p>to higher trophic levels the energy fixed by plants.  When we think
</p>
<p>of predator and prey, most probably it is the tiger and the deer that
</p>
<p>readily come to our mind, but a sparrow eating any seed is no less
</p>
<p>a predator.  Although animals eating plants are categorised
</p>
<p>separately as herbivores, they are, in a broad ecological context,
</p>
<p>not very different from predators.
</p>
<p>Besides acting as ‘conduits’ for energy transfer across trophic
</p>
<p>levels, predators play other important roles.  They keep prey
</p>
<p>populations under control. But for predators, prey species could
</p>
<p>achieve very high population densities and cause ecosystem
</p>
<p>instability. When certain exotic species are introduced into a
</p>
<p>geographical area, they become invasive and start spreading fast
</p>
<p>because the invaded land does not have its natural predators. The
</p>
<p>prickly pear cactus introduced into Australia in the early 1920’s
</p>
<p>caused havoc by spreading rapidly into millions of hectares of
</p>
<p>rangeland.  Finally, the invasive cactus was brought under control
</p>
<p>only after a cactus-feeding predator (a moth) from its natural habitat
</p>
<p>was introduced into the country. Biological control methods adopted
</p>
<p>in agricultural pest control are based on the ability of the predator
</p>
<p>to regulate prey population. Predators also help in maintaining
</p>
<p>species diversity in a community, by reducing the intensity of
</p>
<p>competition among competing prey species.   In the rocky intertidal
</p>
<p>communities of the American Pacific Coast the starfish Pisaster is
</p>
<p>an important predator. In a field experiment, when all the starfish
</p>
<p>were removed from an enclosed intertidal area, more than 10 species
</p>
<p>of invertebrates became extinct within a year, because of inter-
</p>
<p>specific competition.
</p>
<p>If a predator is too efficient and overexploits its prey, then the
</p>
<p>prey might become extinct and following it, the predator will also
</p>
<p>become extinct for lack of food. This is the reason why predators in
</p>
<p>nature are ‘prudent’. Prey species have evolved various defenses to
</p>
<p>lessen the impact of predation.  Some species of insects and frogs
</p>
<p>are cryptically-coloured (camouflaged) to avoid being detected easily
</p>
<p>by the predator. Some are poisonous and therefore avoided by the
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>234
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>predators.  The Monarch butterfly is highly distasteful to its predator
</p>
<p>(bird) because of a special chemical present in its body.
</p>
<p>Interestingly, the butterfly acquires this chemical during its
</p>
<p>caterpillar stage by feeding on a poisonous weed.
</p>
<p>For plants, herbivores are the predators. Nearly 25 per cent of
</p>
<p>all insects are known to be phytophagous (feeding on plant sap
</p>
<p>and other parts of plants).  The problem is particularly severe for
</p>
<p>plants because, unlike animals, they cannot run away from their
</p>
<p>predators. Plants therefore have evolved an astonishing variety of
</p>
<p>morphological and chemical defences against herbivores. Thorns
</p>
<p>(Acacia, Cactus) are the most common morphological means of
</p>
<p>defence. Many plants produce and store chemicals that make the
</p>
<p>herbivore sick when they are eaten, inhibit feeding or digestion,
</p>
<p>disrupt its reproduction or even kill it.  You must have seen the
</p>
<p>weed Calotropis growing in abandoned fields.  The plant produces
</p>
<p>highly poisonous cardiac glycosides and that is why you never see
</p>
<p>any cattle or goats browsing on this plant.  A wide variety of chemical
</p>
<p>substances that we extract from plants on a commercial scale
</p>
<p>(nicotine, caffeine, quinine, strychnine, opium, etc.,) are produced
</p>
<p>by them actually as defences against grazers and browsers.
</p>
<p>(ii) Competition: When Darwin spoke of the struggle for existence and
</p>
<p>survival of the fittest in nature, he was convinced that interspecific
</p>
<p>competition is a potent force in organic evolution. It is generally
</p>
<p>believed that competition occurs when closely related species
</p>
<p>compete for the same resources that are limiting, but this is not
</p>
<p>entirely true. Firstly, totally unrelated species could also compete
</p>
<p>for the same resource. For instance, in some shallow South
</p>
<p>American lakes visiting flamingoes and resident fishes compete for
</p>
<p>their common food, the zooplankton in the lake. Secondly,
</p>
<p>resources need not be limiting for competition to occur; in
</p>
<p>interference competition, the feeding efficiency of one species might
</p>
<p>be reduced due to the interfering and inhibitory presence of the
</p>
<p>other species, even if resources (food and space) are abundant.
</p>
<p>Therefore, competition is best defined as a process in which the
</p>
<p>fitness of one species (measured in terms of its ‘r’ the intrinsic rate
</p>
<p>of increase) is significantly lower in the presence of another species.
</p>
<p>It is relatively easy to demonstrate in laboratory experiments, as
</p>
<p>Gause and other experimental ecologists did,  when resources are
</p>
<p>limited the competitively superior species will eventually eliminate
</p>
<p>the other species, but evidence for such competitive exclusion
</p>
<p>occurring in nature is not always conclusive.  Strong and persuasive
</p>
<p>circumstantial evidence does exist however in some cases. The
</p>
<p>Abingdon tortoise in Galapagos Islands became extinct within a
</p>
<p>decade after goats were introduced on the island, apparently due
</p>
<p>to the greater browsing efficiency of the goats. Another evidence for
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>235
</p>
<p>ORGANISMS AND POPULATIONS
</p>
<p>the occurrence of competition in nature comes from what is called
</p>
<p>‘competitive release’. A species whose distribution is restricted to a
</p>
<p>small geographical area because of the presence of a competitively
</p>
<p>superior species, is found to expand its distributional range
</p>
<p>dramatically when the competing species is experimentally removed.
</p>
<p>Connell’s elegant field experiments showed that on the rocky sea
</p>
<p>coasts of Scotland, the larger and competitively superior barnacle
</p>
<p>Balanus dominates the intertidal area, and excludes the smaller
</p>
<p>barnacle Chathamalus from that zone.  In general, herbivores and
</p>
<p>plants appear to be more adversely affected by competition than
</p>
<p>carnivores.
</p>
<p>Gause’s ‘Competitive Exclusion Principle’ states that two
</p>
<p>closely related species competing for the same resources cannot
</p>
<p>co-exist indefinitely and the competitively inferior one will be
</p>
<p>eliminated eventually. This may be true if resources are limiting,
</p>
<p>but not otherwise. More recent studies do not support such gross
</p>
<p>generalisations about competition.  While they do not rule out the
</p>
<p>occurrence of interspecific competition in nature, they point out
</p>
<p>that species facing competition might evolve mechanisms that
</p>
<p>promote co-existence rather than exclusion. One such mechanism
</p>
<p>is ‘resource partitioning’. If two species compete for the same
</p>
<p>resource, they could avoid competition by choosing, for instance,
</p>
<p>different times for   feeding or different foraging patterns.  MacArthur
</p>
<p>showed that five closely related species of warblers living on the
</p>
<p>same tree were able to avoid competition and co-exist due to
</p>
<p>behavioural differences in their foraging activities.
</p>
<p>(iii) Parasitism: Considering that the parasitic mode of life ensures
</p>
<p>free lodging and meals, it is not surprising that parasitism has
</p>
<p>evolved in so many taxonomic groups from plants to higher
</p>
<p>vertebrates.  Many parasites have evolved to be host-specific (they
</p>
<p>can parasitise only a single species of host) in such a way that both
</p>
<p>host and the parasite tend to co-evolve; that is, if the host evolves
</p>
<p>special mechanisms for rejecting or resisting the parasite, the
</p>
<p>parasite has to evolve mechanisms to counteract and neutralise
</p>
<p>them, in order to be successful with the same host species. In
</p>
<p>accordance with their life styles, parasites evolved special
</p>
<p>adaptations such as the loss of unnecessary sense organs, presence
</p>
<p>of adhesive organs or suckers to cling on to the host, loss of digestive
</p>
<p>system and high reproductive capacity. The life cycles of parasites
</p>
<p>are often complex, involving one or two intermediate hosts or vectors
</p>
<p>to facilitate parasitisation of its primary host. The human liver fluke
</p>
<p>(a trematode parasite) depends on two intermediate hosts (a snail
</p>
<p>and a fish) to complete its life cycle.  The malarial parasite needs a
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>236
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>vector (mosquito) to spread to other hosts.  Majority of the parasites
</p>
<p>harm the host; they may reduce the survival, growth and
</p>
<p>reproduction of the host and reduce its population density. They
</p>
<p>might render the host more vulnerable to predation by making it
</p>
<p>physically weak. Do you believe that an ideal parasite should be
</p>
<p>able to thrive within the host without harming it? Then why didn’t
</p>
<p>natural selection lead to the evolution of such totally harmless
</p>
<p>parasites?
</p>
<p>Parasites that feed on the external surface of the host organism
</p>
<p>are called ectoparasites. The most familiar examples of this group
</p>
<p>are the lice on humans and ticks on dogs. Many marine fish are
</p>
<p>infested with ectoparasitic copepods. Cuscuta, a parasitic plant that
</p>
<p>is commonly found growing on hedge plants, has lost its chlorophyll
</p>
<p>and leaves in the course of evolution. It derives its nutrition from
</p>
<p>the host plant which it parasitises. The female mosquito is not
</p>
<p>considered a parasite, although it needs our blood for reproduction.
</p>
<p>Can you explain why?
</p>
<p>In contrast, endoparasites are those that live inside the host
</p>
<p>body at different sites (liver, kidney, lungs, red blood cells, etc.).
</p>
<p>The life cycles of endoparasites are more complex because of their
</p>
<p>extreme specialisation. Their morphological and anatomical features
</p>
<p>are greatly simplified while emphasising their reproductive potential.
</p>
<p>Brood parasitism in birds is a fascinating example of parasitism
</p>
<p>in which the parasitic bird lays its eggs in the nest of its host and
</p>
<p>lets the host incubate them. During the course of evolution, the
</p>
<p>eggs of the parasitic bird have evolved to resemble the host’s egg in
</p>
<p>size and colour to reduce the chances of the host bird detecting the
</p>
<p>foreign eggs and ejecting them from the nest. Try to follow the
</p>
<p>movements of the cuckoo (koel) and the crow in your neighborhood
</p>
<p>park during the breeding season (spring to summer) and watch
</p>
<p>brood parasitism in action.
</p>
<p>(iv) Commensalism: This is the interaction in which one species benefits
</p>
<p>and the other is neither harmed nor benefited. An orchid growing
</p>
<p>as an epiphyte on a mango branch, and barnacles growing on the
</p>
<p>back of a whale benefit while neither the mango tree nor the whale
</p>
<p>derives any apparent benefit.   The cattle egret and grazing cattle in
</p>
<p>close association, a sight you are most likely to catch if you live in
</p>
<p>farmed rural areas, is a classic example of commensalism.  The
</p>
<p>egrets always forage close to where the cattle are grazing because
</p>
<p>the cattle, as they move, stir up and flush out from the vegetation
</p>
<p>insects that otherwise might be difficult for the egrets to find and
</p>
<p>catch.  Another example of commensalism is the interaction between
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>237
</p>
<p>ORGANISMS AND POPULATIONS
</p>
<p>sea anemone that has stinging tentacles and the clown fish that
</p>
<p>lives among them.  The fish gets protection from predators which
</p>
<p>stay away from the stinging tentacles. The anemone does not appear
</p>
<p>to derive any benefit by hosting the clown fish.
</p>
<p>(v) Mutualism: This interaction confers benefits on both the interacting
</p>
<p>species. Lichens represent an intimate mutualistic relationship
</p>
<p>between a fungus and photosynthesising algae or cyanobacteria.
</p>
<p>Similarly, the mycorrhizae are associations between fungi and the
</p>
<p>roots of higher plants. The fungi help the plant in the absorption of
</p>
<p>essential nutrients from the soil while the plant in turn provides the
</p>
<p>fungi with energy-yielding carbohydrates.
</p>
<p>The most spectacular and evolutionarily fascinating examples
</p>
<p>of mutualism are found in plant-animal relationships.  Plants need
</p>
<p>the help of animals for pollinating their flowers and dispersing their
</p>
<p>seeds.  Animals obviously have to be paid ‘fees’ for the services that
</p>
<p>plants expect from them.  Plants offer rewards or fees in the form of
</p>
<p>pollen and nectar for pollinators and juicy and nutritious fruits for
</p>
<p>seed dispersers.  But the mutually beneficial system should also
</p>
<p>be safeguarded against ‘cheaters’, for example, animals that try to
</p>
<p>steal nectar without aiding in pollination. Now you can see why
</p>
<p>plant-animal interactions often involve co-evolution of the
</p>
<p>mutualists, that is, the evolutions of the flower and its pollinator
</p>
<p>species are tightly linked with one another. In many species of fig
</p>
<p>trees, there is a tight one-to-one relationship with the pollinator
</p>
<p>species of wasp (Figure 13.6).  It means that a given fig species can
</p>
<p>be pollinated only by its ‘partner’ wasp species and no other species.
</p>
<p>The female wasp uses the fruit not only as an oviposition (egg-laying)
</p>
<p>site but uses the developing seeds within the fruit for nourishing
</p>
<p>Figure 13.6 Mutual relationship between fig tree and wasp: (a) Fig flower is pollinated
by wasp; (b) Wasp laying eggs in a fig fruit
</p>
<p>(a) (b)
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>238
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>its larvae.  The wasp pollinates the fig inflorescence while
</p>
<p>searching for suitable egg-laying sites. In return for the
</p>
<p>favour of pollination the fig offers the wasp some of its
</p>
<p>developing seeds, as food for the developing wasp larvae.
</p>
<p>Orchids show a bewildering diversity of floral
</p>
<p>patterns many of which have evolved to attract the right
</p>
<p>pollinator insect (bees and bumblebees) and ensure
</p>
<p>guaranteed pollination by it (Figure 13.7). Not all
</p>
<p>orchids offer rewards. The Mediterranean orchid
</p>
<p>Ophrys employs ‘sexual deceit’ to get pollination done
</p>
<p>by a species of bee.  One petal of its flower bears an
</p>
<p>uncanny resemblance to the female of the bee in size,
</p>
<p>colour and markings. The male bee is attracted to what
</p>
<p>it perceives as a female, ‘pseudocopulates’ with the
</p>
<p>flower, and during that process is dusted with pollen
</p>
<p>from the flower. When this same bee ‘pseudocopulates’
</p>
<p>with another flower, it transfers pollen to it and thus,
</p>
<p>pollinates the flower. Here you can see how co-evolution
</p>
<p>operates. If the female bee’s colour patterns change even slightly for any
</p>
<p>reason during evolution, pollination success will be reduced unless the
</p>
<p>orchid flower co-evolves to maintain the resemblance of its petal to the
</p>
<p>female bee.
</p>
<p>Figure 13.7 Showing bee-a pollinator
on orchid flower
</p>
<p>SUMMARY
</p>
<p>As a branch of biology, Ecology is the study of the relationships of
</p>
<p>living organisms with the abiotic (physico-chemical factors) and biotic
</p>
<p>components (other species) of their environment. It is concerned
</p>
<p>with four levels of biological organisation-organisms, populations,
</p>
<p>communities and biomes.
</p>
<p>Temperature, light, water and soil are the most important
</p>
<p>physical factors of the environment to which the organisms are
</p>
<p>adapted in various ways. Maintenance of a constant internal
</p>
<p>environment (homeostasis) by the organisms contributes to optimal
</p>
<p>performance, but only some organisms (regulators) are capable of
</p>
<p>homeostasis in the face of changing external environment. Others
</p>
<p>either partially regulate their internal environment or simply
</p>
<p>conform. A few other species have evolved adaptations to avoid
</p>
<p>unfavourable conditions in space (migration) or in time (aestivation,
</p>
<p>hibernation, and diapause).
</p>
<p>Evolutionary changes through natural selection take place at
</p>
<p>the population level and hence, population ecology is an important
</p>
<p>area of ecology. A population is a group of individuals of a given
</p>
<p>species sharing or competing for similar resources in a defined
</p>
<p>geographical area. Populations have attributes that individual
</p>
<p>organisms do not- birth rates and death rates, sex ratio and age
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>239
</p>
<p>ORGANISMS AND POPULATIONS
</p>
<p>distribution. The proportion of different age groups of males and
</p>
<p>females in a population is often presented graphically as age pyramid;
</p>
<p>its shape indicates whether a population is stationary, growing or
</p>
<p>declining.
</p>
<p>Ecological effects of any factors on a population are generally
</p>
<p>reflected in its size (population density), which may be expressed in
</p>
<p>different ways (numbers, biomass, per cent cover, etc.,) depending
</p>
<p>on the species.
</p>
<p>Populations grow through births and immigration and decline
</p>
<p>through deaths and emigration.  When resources are unlimited, the
</p>
<p>growth is usually exponential but when resources become
</p>
<p>progressively limiting, the growth pattern turns logistic. In either
</p>
<p>case, growth is ultimately limited by the carrying capacity of the
</p>
<p>environment. The intrinsic rate of natural increase (r) is a measure
</p>
<p>of the inherent potential of a population to grow.
</p>
<p>In nature populations of different species in a habitat do not live
</p>
<p>in isolation but interact in many ways.  Depending on the outcome,
</p>
<p>these interactions between two species are classified as competition
</p>
<p>(both species suffer), predation and parasitism (one benefits and the
</p>
<p>other suffers), commensalism (one benefits and the other is
</p>
<p>unaffected), amensalism (one is harmed, other unaffected) and
</p>
<p>mutualism (both species benefit).  Predation is a very important
</p>
<p>process through which trophic energy transfer is facilitated and some
</p>
<p>predators help in controlling their prey populations. Plants have
</p>
<p>evolved diverse morphological and chemical defenses against
</p>
<p>herbivory.  In competition, it is presumed that the superior competitor
</p>
<p>eliminates the inferior one (the Competitive Exclusion Principle), but
</p>
<p>many closely related species have evolved various mechanisms which
</p>
<p>facilitate their co-existence. Some of the most fascinating cases of
</p>
<p>mutualism in nature are seen in plant-pollinator interactions.
</p>
<p>EXERCISES
1. How is diapause different from hibernation?
</p>
<p>2. If a marine fish is placed in a fresh water aquarium, will the fish be
</p>
<p>able to survive? Why or why not?
</p>
<p>3. Define phenotypic adaptation. Give one example.
</p>
<p>4. Most living organisms cannot survive at temperature above 450C. How
</p>
<p>are some microbes able to live in habitats with temperatures exceeding
</p>
<p>1000C?
</p>
<p>5. List the attributes that populations but not individuals possess.
</p>
<p>6. If a population growing exponentially double in size in 3 years, what is
</p>
<p>the intrinsic rate of increase (r) of the population?
</p>
<p>7. Name important defence mechanisms in plants against herbivory.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="page"><p/>
<p>240
</p>
<p>BIOLOGY
</p>
<p>8. An orchid plant is growing on the branch of mango tree. How do you
</p>
<p>describe this interaction between the orchid and the mango tree?
</p>
<p>9. What is the ecological principle behind the biological control method of
</p>
<p>managing with pest insects?
</p>
<p>10. Distinguish between the following:
</p>
<p>(a) Hibernation and Aestivation
</p>
<p>(b) Ectotherms and Endotherms
</p>
<p>11. Write a short note on
</p>
<p>(a) Adaptations of desert plants and animals
</p>
<p>(b) Adaptations of plants to water scarcity
</p>
<p>(c) Behavioural adaptations in animals
</p>
<p>(d) Importance of light to plants
</p>
<p>(e) Effect of temperature or water scarcity and the adaptations of animals.
</p>
<p>12. List the various abiotic environmental factors.
</p>
<p>13. Give an example for:
</p>
<p>(a) An endothermic animal
</p>
<p>(b) An ectothermic animal
</p>
<p>(c) An organism of benthic zone
</p>
<p>14. Define population and community.
</p>
<p>15. Define the following terms and give one example for each:
</p>
<p>(a) Commensalism
</p>
<p>(b) Parasitism
</p>
<p>(c) Camouflage
</p>
<p>(d) Mutualism
</p>
<p>(e) Interspecific competition
</p>
<p>16. With the help of suitable diagram describe the logistic population
</p>
<p>growth curve.
</p>
<p>17. Select the statement which explains best parasitism.
</p>
<p>(a) One organism is benefited.
</p>
<p>(b) Both the organisms are benefited.
</p>
<p>(c) One organism is benefited, other is not affected.
</p>
<p>(d) One organism is benefited, other is affected.
</p>
<p>18. List any three important characteristics of a population and explain.
</p>
<p>2015-16</p>
<p/>
</div>
<div class="acroform"><ol/>
</div>
</body></html>